<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatyse of Chris[ti]an peregrination, w[rit]ten by M. Gregory Martin Licentiate, and late reader of the diuinitie in the Englishe Coleadge at Remes. VVhereunto is adioined certen epistles vvritten by him to sundrye his frendes: the copies vvhereof vvere since him decease founde amonge his vvrytings. Novv especially published for the beneifte of those, that either erre in religion of simplicitie or folovv the vvorlde of fray Ioie</title>
            <author>Martin, Gregory, d. 1582.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17507</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102523</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838300</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838300</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07104)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1108:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatyse of Chris[ti]an peregrination, w[rit]ten by M. Gregory Martin Licentiate, and late reader of the diuinitie in the Englishe Coleadge at Remes. VVhereunto is adioined certen epistles vvritten by him to sundrye his frendes: the copies vvhereof vvere since him decease founde amonge his vvrytings. Novv especially published for the beneifte of those, that either erre in religion of simplicitie or folovv the vvorlde of fray Ioie</title>
                  <author>Martin, Gregory, d. 1582.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[140] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For R. Verstegan],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini 1583 [i.e. ca. 1597]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: pi²  A-E [F-I K⁴].</note>
                  <note>Place of publication, printer's name and actual publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Christian peregrination.</note>
                  <note>"A letter sente by M. Licentiate Martin to a maried priest his frende" has caption title; neither signed nor paginated.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; preliminary leaves tightly bound; title page cropped, stained and torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pilgrims and pilgrimages --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Pilgrims and pilgrimages --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Relics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Relics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reliquaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reliquaries --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATYSE OF CHRI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>AN PEREGRINATION, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ten by M. Gregory Martin Licentiate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and late reader of diuinitie in the Engliſhe Coleadge at Remes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhereunto is adioined certen Epiſtles vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by him to ſundrye his frendes: the copies vvhereof vvere ſince his deceaſe founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge his vvrytinges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Novv eſpecially pupliſhed for the banifite, of thoſe, that either erre in religion of ſimplicitie, or folovv the vvorlde of frayl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO DOMINI</hi> 1583.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The contentes of this booke.</head>
            <p>A briefe preface.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A treatiſe of Pilgrimage and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A letter ſente to M. N. a maried prieſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A letter ſent to his Siſters, maried to proteſtants, and them ſelues trained vpp in hereſie, where he ſheweth and proueth the Catholicke Church to be the true Church.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A letter ſent to M. D. Whyte then warden of newe colleadge in Oxford, touching his folow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the worlde and diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbling in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and knowledge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:3"/>
            <head>The Printers Preface vnto the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE aunciente Authour of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by innumerable meanes endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his inſtruments (the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed enimies of Catholicke truth) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eruerſly to opugne by flat denyall, impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to vvreſt by abſurde cauills, or Ievviſhly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reiecte vvith blaſphemous tauntes, thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inges vvhich either they liſte not to beleeue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſire not to learne: In all vvhich, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir facilitie vvere euer n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>torious, yet their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pudencie vvas neuer more manifeſt then in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is age. But ſeeing truth is eterall, hereſie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ariable, and incredulitie atbiſme: The mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs of Chriſt his Catholicke Church on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſide being guided by the holy Ghoſt, haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſeaſed ſufficiently to circumuent and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer the finall driftes of thoſe deluders in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y moſt excellent and learned diſcourſes late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vvritten, amonge the vvhich this briefe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reatyſe of Chriſtian Peregrynation</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me vnto my handes; the vvhich by lycenſe
<pb facs="tcp:2674:4"/>of my Superiours, I haue here publiſhed, and annexed there-unto certayne Epiſtles of the ſame Authors, a man of rare vertue and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent learning. Leauing thee (good Chriſtian Reader) vvith attention to conſider thereof: truſting the ſame vvill ſufficiently geue teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie vnto thee, that there is no parte or poy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Catholicke Fayth vnable inuincibly to be defended. Further aſſuring thee, that vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer incredulous hereticke gayn-ſayeth the ſame, he not onely reſiſteth here in earth the Church millitant and the members therof, but violently ſtryueth agaynſt the Prophetes, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Fathers, Doctours and bleſſed Sayntes in heauen, vvhoſe very vvords and vvrytings here alleadged he vvickedly oppugneth, the vvhich action of his and compariſon of him vvith thoſe, may be a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente motiue to confirme thy fayth. Vale.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:4"/>
            <head>A SHORTE DISCOVRSE OF Pilgrimage and Relycks.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>ILGRYMAGE co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge of the latyne worde <hi>perigrinatio,</hi> is nothinge ells in this preſente caſe which now I mene to write of,
<note place="margin">The name of pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage &amp; pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grime.</note> but going of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tion to viſite ſome holy monument <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Chriſt or his Saints, as to <hi>Hieruſalem, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rome,</hi> to <hi>Compoſtella.</hi> To the which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aces becauſe there hath bene alwaies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat reſort of ſtrangers (in latin <hi>pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ini</hi>) out of all Chriſtian countries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erof is it that we ſay, <hi>Pilgrimes</hi> of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſalem,</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> of <hi>Compoſtella,</hi> that is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raungers and religious trauelers to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe places. For example, wheras the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ree wyſe and honorable perſons na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed <hi>Magi</hi> came from the Eaſte to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ip Chriſt in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 2.</note> we may very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uely ſay of them, that they came in
<pb facs="tcp:2674:5"/>Pilgrimage to Chriſt. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlayne to the Queene of <hi>Aethiopr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> whom <hi>Philippe</hi> baptiſed, went out of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> countrye to worſhip God in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> he wente alſo in Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage. <hi>S. Paule</hi> him ſelfe goinge to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> of purpoſe to ſee <hi>Peter,</hi> and (as <hi>Theophylactus</hi> noteth) <hi>not to ſee him onely,
<note place="margin">In. 1. Galat.</note> but vvith all to honour him as his be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, euen as vve goe to holy vertuous men,</hi> made a certeyne Pilgrimage. The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is, here was Pilgrimage to the perſons them ſelues, as to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and to <hi>Peter,</hi> we hauing now their monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts onely and of other Saints, make Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage vnto them.
<note place="margin">Ho. 5. ad po. Antioch.</note> And accordinge to this ſenſe <hi>S. Chriſoſtome</hi> in one of his Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s moſt properly ſpeaketh thus. <hi>If I vvere voyde of Eccleſiaſticall cares and had a ſtrong body, I vvould not refuſe to make ſoe longe a iourney,</hi> (as from Antioch to Rome) <hi>to ſee the cheynes at the leaſt and the priſon, vvhere Paule vvas bound.</hi> In the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin we read it thus, <hi>peregrinationem tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam facere non recuſarem.</hi> I woulde not
<pb facs="tcp:2674:5"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cke to make ſo longe a Pilgrimage. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd this much for the names of Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime and Pilgrimage, which heretiks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue made ſore bugges-wordes, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ough a man would ſaye, Idolatour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Idolattie.</p>
            <p>Which termes to the ende thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yeſt vnderſtand (Chriſtian Reader) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w falſely and fooliſhly they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted to vs:
<note place="margin">The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal cauſe of pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, Gods honor.</note> Marke in all that I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hereafter, the feruent deuotion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>grymes, and the princypall cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reof, to wit the glory of God and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> honour of his Sonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich are the very grounds of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke Pilgrimage,
<note place="margin">Ho. 5. ad Po. Antioch.</note> Deuotion or affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, as when the forſayed holy Doctor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ulpet vehemently brake out into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe words: <hi>Vellem nunc in illis locis ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. I vvould vviſh novv to be for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in the places vvhere theſe chaynes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yne, and ſee the fetters, vvhich diuels feare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Angels reuerence.</hi> The cauſe of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> affection, becauſe they were <hi>Paules</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynes, his cheynes that was <hi>Vas electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:6"/>
               <note place="margin">God chefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when ſayntes or their reliks are honoted</note> Gods choſen veſſell: his cheyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that caried the name of Chriſt before Kinges and countryes, that turned a great parte of the worlde to the fayth, that wrote ſo many excellent Epiſtles for our edifying, that for Chriſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red infinit miſeries, finally his cheynes that vnder <hi>Nero</hi> ſhed his bloud for the Ghoſpell. Theſe conſiderations and the lyke made this learned Father ſo in loue with the Apoſtle, that he could not conteyne him ſelfe, but woulde needes ſignifie, how he honored the very fetters, cordes, and linckes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with this Champion was tyed for the name of Chriſt. This religious zeale towardes Chriſt and his Saynts cauſed him in an other place to ſaye in this heauenly maner. <hi>I remember thee Peter, and am amaſed. I thinke vpon thee Paule, and being in maner paſt my ſelfe, can not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayne vveeping, for vvhat I may ſay or vvhat I may ſpeake beholding your afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I knovv not. Hovv many priſons haue you ſanctified? Hovv many cheynes haue you
<pb facs="tcp:2674:6"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eautified? Hovv many tormentes haue you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uſteyned? You haue folovved Chriſt in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings. VVell mayeſt thou reioyſe Peter, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adſt the gift to ſuffer vpon the Croſſe as Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>id. Bleſſed are the nayles that perſed thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly limmes of thyne. Thou alſo (O bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aule) haſte greate cauſe to be glad, vvhoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead vvas cut of vvith the ſvvord. VVhat a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>recious ſvvord is that vvhich perced thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red throte, the inſtrument of our Lord, vvhich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eauen doth admire, and the earth doth reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence. That ſvvord I vvish to be my garland, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd thoſo nayles of Peter in ſteed of precious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nes to ſtande in my golden crovvne.</hi> This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euotion proceding of that cauſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eferred to that end, which is the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hip and glory of Chriſt, is the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>round of honoring Relicks, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>equentlye the cauſe of Pilgrimage: The glory of Chriſt I ſay.
<note place="margin">1. cor. 3.</note> For <hi>vvhat is Paule, vvhat Apollo, vvhat Peter, but his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iniſters and ſeruantes in vvhom vve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeue?</hi> Our Sauiour ſayeth, he that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a cuppe of could water to one of his litle ones, <hi>tantum in nomine diſcipuli,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:7"/>onely in the name of a diſciple, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>S. Marke</hi> expreſſeth it,
<note place="margin">Cap. 9.</note> 
               <hi>quia Chriſti ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> becauſe they belong to Chriſt, he ſhall not looſe his rewarde. And he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth a Prophete <hi>in nomine Propheta,</hi> becauſe he is a Prophete, not for an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other worldly conſideration, he ſhall haue a rewarde anſwerable to the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of a Prophete.
<note place="margin">Li. 4. cap. 4.</note> We reade in the bookes of Kinges, that the welthy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Suna</hi> hauing entertayned <hi>Eli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> at length ſayed to her huſband <hi>I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue this is a holy man of God vvhich paſſeth by our hovvſe ſo often: let vs therefore prouide a litle chamber for him, and ſet a hed in it, a table, a ſtoole, and a candleſticke, that he may reſt vvith vs, vvhen be commeth.</hi> Therefore (ſayeth ſhe) let vs doe it, becauſe he is a holy man of God. A goodly reaſon and godly conſideration. But what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde had ſhe? Being barren before, now ſhe had a ſonne: the ſonne dyed, and was reſtored to lyfe agayne, that after ſorow her ioy might be greater. In the greate dearth that then happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:7"/>ſhe was well prouided for in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther countrye, and after ſeuen yeres receaueth all her poſſeſſions agayne, and the rents for the tyme that ſhe was abſent, by the Kings commaundment, and all this by the meanes of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete whom ſhe ſo entertayned. <hi>Leoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> father to <hi>Origen</hi> that learned Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, him ſelfe a great clerke and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a Martyr, was wonte to kiſſe his ſonnes breſt, being then a litle boye, when he laye ſleeping.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſeb. li. 6, cap. 2.</note> If therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was his prety boy, it had bene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> litle fondnes, but the ſtorye ſayeth: <hi>Oſculabatur tanquam Spiritus ſancti habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aculum:
<note place="margin">Hiero. in. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pitaphio.</note> He kiſſed it as the dvvelling or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the holy Ghoſt. Paula</hi> an honotable widow and religious marrone of <hi>Rome</hi> comming in Pilgrimage to <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> after many godly meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, at length concludeth thus. <hi>Here is my reſting place, becauſe it is the country of my Lord: here vvil I dvvell, becauſe our Sauioer hath choſen it. S. Hierome</hi> ſpeking of <hi>Origens</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries vpon the twelue Prophets,
<note place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:2674:8"/>that he eſteemed them as much worth as <hi>Craeſus</hi> welth. Whye? becauſe they were written with <hi>Pamphilus</hi> the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs owne hand. <hi>Si enim laetitia eſt &amp;c. For if it be great ioye to haue one epiſtle of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, hovv much more, to haue ſo many thovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand verſes, vvhich I imagine as though they vvere dravvne vvith the printes of his bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This deuotion toward God and his ſonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> maketh holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to honour all thinges that belong to them.
<note place="margin">The trewe end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pilgrims.</note> Prophetes, becauſe they are Gods Prophets. Mattyrs, becauſe they are the matyrs of Chriſt. All monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of them, for their ſake. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning places: <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> becauſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour was borne there. <hi>Mount Caluarye,</hi> becauſe he ſuffred there. <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paule</hi> are buried there, there they dyed for Chriſt, there are their bodies, their ſhrynes, their chaynes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their glorious memories. In this reſpect to goe to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> to trauaile to <hi>Rome,</hi> is a very frutefull Pilgrimage. Otherwiſe to goe to ſee ſtrange coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:8"/>gaye buildinges, prophane anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, to learne tongues, yea and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome traytours doe, to eſpye faultes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ometyme it is ſinfull, and neuer to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alled Pilgrimage.
<note place="margin">Socrat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. ca. 18.</note> It is tould much for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he prayſe of <hi>Ammonius</hi> an auncionte monke, that going to <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atius,</hi> he was ſo farre from all vayne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urioſitie, that he deſired to ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing at all of the ſtately buildinges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here, but onely <hi>Peter &amp; Paules</hi> Church: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arre contrary to a certen countrye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of ours, whoe making large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orts of courtyſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, what goodly how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and how many they had, wherin by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he authority of a traueler he thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e might bouldly feyne at his pleaſure: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing demaunded of a wyſe man, how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any Churches were there, how bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifull, how deuoutly frequented, could make no anſwere. Such a wonderfull difference there is betweene a good godly Pilgrime, and a worldly wicked traueler.
<note place="margin">In Ep. ad. Rom.</note> 
               <hi>S. Chriſoſtome</hi> declaring his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler affection toward <hi>Rome,</hi> hath after
<pb facs="tcp:2674:9"/>his maner theſe excellente wordes. <hi>I therefore loue Rome (albeit I might prayſe it for other cauſes, for largenes, for antiquitie, for beautie, for number of people, for the Empyre, for ryches, for mightye thinges atcheiued in vvarfare, but letting paſſe all theſe, therefore I accompt it a bleſſed Cyttie,) becauſe Paule did ſo loue them, vvhen he lyued, and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before them, and at length ended his lyfe among them: vvhoſe holy body they haue, and therfore that Cittie thereby is made more glorious, then by all other thinges. And as it vvere a great mightye bodye that had tvvo gliftering eyes, ſo it hath the bodyes of thoſe Saints</hi> (Peter and Paule): <hi>The heauens I tell you doe not ſo ſhyne, vvhen the ſunne caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his beames, as doth the Cyttie of Rome vvith theſe lampes, that lighten the vvhole vvorld. Conſider me I pray you, and be ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to thinke, vvhat a fight Rome ſhall ſee vvhen Paule ſhall ryſe ſodenly out of that Coffin of his, vvith Peter, to meete our Lorde. O that I might be ſo haeppie as to embrace and grype that body of Paule rounde about, to be tyed in his graue a vvhyle, to ſee but the duſte
<pb facs="tcp:2674:9"/>of that bodye vvhich caried the markes of Chriſt.</hi> Tell me (gentle Reader) when thou heareſt this, art thou not moued with deuotion towarde the very car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſes of thoſe Apoſtles, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly toward the Cittie where they are to be ſeene? I confeſſe vnto thee my fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh kind harte in this caſe: As often as I reade it I am redy to melte for ioye. But marke as I began to ſay the cauſe of his affection towarde <hi>Rome:</hi> to wit the bodies of the Apoſtles lying there, and why the bodies? becauſe they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the markes of Chriſt. This is it that cauſeth Pilgrimage. This conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<note place="margin">The eruen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deuotion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pilgrimes whence it procedeth.</note> for the loue of Chriſt and the honour of him, inflamed this godly Father and all the beſte Chriſtians in the Primitiue Church, to loue ſacred monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to be deſirous to ſee them, to goe farre and neere vnto them, to touch, to kiſſe, to licke them, to weepe in the place, to conceaue ſuch a lyuely imagination of thinges done there by Chriſt or his Saynts, and withall ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:2674:10"/>a ſenſible feeling of heauenly deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it was a payne to remoue from thence, a death to dwell farre of: A ioy and comfort to ſay with the Spouſe of Chriſt, <hi>Inueni quem quaeſiuit anima mea: te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebo eum &amp; non dimittam.</hi> I haue founde him whom my ſoule ſought for. I will hould him faſt, and neuer let him goe. One example may ſuffice in ſteede of a number, being of moſt excellent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, and therefore I will tell it at large and neuer craue pardon for the matter, becauſe I know it can not but much delight al ſuch as are not ſworne ennemies to the honour of Chriſt and his ſacred monuments.</p>
            <p>I named a litle before one <hi>Paula</hi> a verye honorable gentle-woman of <hi>Rome:</hi> who after the death of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande entred into religion with her doughter <hi>Euſtochium,</hi> traueled both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to the holy lande, dwelt there aboue twentie yeres, vntill her death. Whoſe vertues vere ſuch that <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> doth proteſt, if all his ioyntes and
<pb facs="tcp:2674:10"/>limmes were turned into tongues, he could not ſufficiently prayſe her: and calleth IESVS to witnes, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he wryteth of her, is a playne hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricall truth, and no retoricall ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.
<note place="margin">In Epita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phio.</note> The order of her Pilgrimage for the cheefe points was this as <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> telleth it.
<note place="margin">The pilgri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mage of paula.</note> After ſhe had paſſed <hi>Rhodes</hi> and <hi>Lycia,</hi> ſhe came at length to <hi>Cypres,</hi> where ſhe fell at the feete of the holy and reuerent Biſhop <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> and was content to be ſtayed there ten dayes, not to reſt her in ſteed of a bayt, but to doe workes of charitie: For in that ſpace ſhe viſited all the religious howſes of that country,
<note place="margin">Cypres fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of religion men.</note> and as ſhe was able, gaue them almes: From thence ſhe made a litle cutte ouer the water to <hi>Selencia</hi> and ſo to <hi>Antioch,</hi> where the holy Confeſſour <hi>Paulinus</hi> could ſtaye her but a very litle tyme: but euen in the mids of winter (ſo feruent ſhe was in fayth) a woman of honorable cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, tooke her iorney vpon a lytle aſſe: Arryueth at <hi>Sarepta,</hi> where ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb facs="tcp:2674:11"/>into a litle turret of <hi>Elias,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her prayers to our Sauiour, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by the ſandes at the ſhore of <hi>Tyre</hi> where <hi>Paule</hi> kneeled: From thence to <hi>Caeſaria:</hi> In it ſhe ſaw <hi>Cornelius</hi> howſe, whoſe houſhold was the litle Church of Chriſt: and <hi>Phillips</hi> chambers with the fowre cloſettes of his doughters that were Virgins and Prophets: Then to <hi>Nicopolis,</hi> which before was called <hi>Emaus,</hi> where our Sauiour was know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in the breaking of bread. To make ſhorte,
<note place="margin">Hermynd was onlie to ſacred monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> ſhe forſooke the princely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numente of Queene <hi>Helena</hi> (who had ſuccoured the people with corne in a tyme of famine) and went on ſtreyght to <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> The Lieutenante of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine</hi> knowing her howſe and family very well, commaunded the Palace to be prepared for her, but ſhe choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a litle baſe cottage, and with ſuch feruente deuotion viſited euery holy place, that but for haſtening to the reſt ſhe might hardly haue bene plucked from the former. In <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:2674:11"/>before the <hi>Croſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Her manner of reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in holy places.</note> euen as though ſhe had ſeene our Lord preſent, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly ſhe adored and did humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence. Entring into the <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> ſhe kiſſed the <hi>Reſurrection-ſtone,</hi> which the Angell had remoued from the doore: and the very place where our Lords body did lye, ſhe licked with a fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mouth, as one that thirſted after water much longed for. All <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> beareth witnes, what teares, what ſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binge, what ſorowe ſhe powred out there: Our Lord him ſelfe is witnes to whom ſhe prayed. Comminge furth from thence, ſhe went to <hi>Sion,</hi> which is (to interpret) a peere or watch-tower: there was ſhewed vnto her a piller that bare vp part of the cloyſter, embrued with our Lords bloud, to the which they ſay he was tyed and whipte. The place was ſhewed where the holye Ghoſte came downe vpon a hundred and twentie perſons that beleeued, to the fulfilling of <hi>Ioels</hi> Propheſie. This donne, ſhe deuided the litle ſubſtance
<pb facs="tcp:2674:12"/>ſhe had to the poore Pilgrimes there her felow-ſeruants, and went forward to <hi>Bethlehem.</hi> In the way at the righte hand ſhe pawſed at <hi>Rachels</hi> ſepulcher, where ſhe was deliuered of <hi>Beniamin:</hi> From thence being entred into <hi>Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem,</hi> after ſhe ſaw once the Inne of the bleſſed Virgin, and that ſtall where the oxe did acknowledge his lord and the aſſe his maiſters ſtable,
<note place="margin">Wonderfull deuotion by occaſion of the plrce.</note> ſhe ſware in my hearing (ſayeth <hi>S. Hierome</hi>) that ſhe ſaw with the eyes of faith, the Infant wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in his clowtes, our Lord crying in his cradle, the wyſe men adoring, the ſtarre ſhining ouer the howſe, the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mother, the carefull Tutour, the ſhe pheards comming in the night to ſee what the matter was, the yong In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentes ſlayne: <hi>Herode</hi> raging, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> flying into <hi>Egipte:</hi> wherat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene teares and ioy ſhe brake furth into theſe words,
<note place="margin">So the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew words do ſignifye.</note> ſaying: <hi>All bayle Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem the verye hovvſe of bread in deede,</hi> wherein was borne that bread which came downe from heauen. All hayle
<pb facs="tcp:2674:12"/>
               <hi>Ephrata, vvorthely called a moſte plentifull and frutefull country,</hi> whoſe fruteful flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is God him ſelfe. Of thee <hi>Micheas</hi> prophicyed long agoe. <hi>And thou Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem the hovvſe of Ephrata, art not the leaſt among a thouſand other in Iuda: out of thee ſhall come ſurth to me euen he that ſhall be prince in Iſraell, vvhoſe proceeding is from the beginning and from the dayes of eternitie.</hi> And I wretched and ſinfull woman that I am, how is it that I am thought worthy to kiſſe the manger where my Lorde firſt cryed, being a litle pretye one, and to pray in that cabbin, where the Virgin Child-wife brought furth our Lord a yong babe? Here is my reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place, becauſe it is my Lords coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye: here will I dwell, becauſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour hath choſen it. Thus farre <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> and much more which I omitte. Tell me Reader who ſo euer thou art, I appeale to thy conſcience: what do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou thinke of this noble womans Pilgrimage? Haſt thou not read here her wonderfull deſire and longing to
<pb facs="tcp:2674:13"/>theſe holy places? her exceeding de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion in them? her words? her teares? her maner of worſhip, in all poyntes ſo feruently and diſcretely applyed to the honor of our Lorde and Sauiour, that to dreame of her ſuperſtition in this caſe, were colde Chriſtianitie: to imagine Idolatrie, were playne infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie? Moſte happie is he that can feele in him ſelfe theſe heauenly motions toward the leaſt thinges that concerne Chriſt, for his ſake: And moſt vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie is he that doth not at the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it: for to diſpyſe and condemne it altogether, I knowe right well is no ſmall poynt of hereſie, but in deede that name is to common and therefore to good for it.</p>
            <p>This this I ſaye, and often I muſt repete it, is the true cauſe, and maner, and frute of Catholicke Pilgrimage, exemplified by me in the forſayd <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pilgrimage to Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem from al countries in al ages.</note> but ſo vniuerſally vſed of all the moſte holy and beſt learned men in the Primitiue Church, that <hi>S. Hierome</hi> in an
<pb facs="tcp:2674:13"/>other place wryteth thus.
<note place="margin">Ad marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam in the name of Paula and Euſtockium.</note> It were long for me to runne through euerye age from the Aſcenſion of our Lord vnto this day, and to ſhew, what Biſhops, what Martyrs, what excellent Diuines haue come in Pilgrimage to <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> thinking that their deuotion and knowledge was ſo much the leſſe, and that they wanted ſome-thing to the perfection of vertue, if they had not worſhipped Chriſt in the ſame places, from whence the Ghoſpell gan firſt to ſhyne downe from of the Croſſe. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the companye of religious perſons both men and women (that haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted thither) is a certayne flower and moſt pretious iewell among the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church.
<note place="margin">pilgrimes of our owne countrye in S. Hieromes tyme.</note> In <hi>Fraunce</hi> who ſoeuer is the cheefe, he commeth hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all haſt. The <hi>Britayne</hi> whom the ſeas deuide from this mayne part of the world that we are in, if he grow once to be any thing religious and well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, he forſaketh the weſt parts, and ſeketh after this place which he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:2674:14"/>by commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brute only &amp; by report of the ſcriptures. What neede I reckon here the <hi>Armenians,</hi> the <hi>Perſians, Indians, Aethiopians,</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> adioyning to it ful of Religious folke, <hi>Pontus,</hi> and <hi>Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docia, Coele-ſyria</hi> and <hi>Meſopotamea</hi> with whole ſwarms of the Eaſt, and ſo furth. Gentle Reder, be wyſe and ſober in eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeming of holye thinges, marke thoſe few examples, and be not wiſe in thine owne ſkoffing conceyte to condemne the authoritie of the whole world, and of that auncyent world, which by our aduerſaries co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion was without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Thow haſt here the cuſtome of all ſtates and degrees, out of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes, ſynce CHRIST aſcended, by S. <hi>Hieromes</hi> accompt. Vnles perhaps thou deſire alſo to heare of Kyngs and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours: which demande is not vnrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable, for that ſome Prynces now a dayes are partly ſo prowd, and partly ſo farre from all deuocion, that it may ſeme incredible that the mightie Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of the world, aboue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:2674:14"/>yeres ago, would not only reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kneele in the place, <hi>Vbi steterunt pedes eius,</hi> where he ſtood, walked, died, roſe againe &amp; aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, that is Lord of lords,
<note place="margin">The Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Princes, and their honor of Relikes.</note> but ſtoupe to the duſt &amp; aſhes of poore fyſhers his Apoſtles, &amp; of meaner men his beloued ſeruants. And yet how ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy it were to be copious in this poynte, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be ignorant, that haue read the eccleſiaſtical hiſtories of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyne the great,</hi> and his mother <hi>Helena,</hi> of <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his ſonne and <hi>Eudocia</hi> the Empereſſe his wyfe, of others. My purpoſe to be ſhort doth not ſuffer me to tell of all perticularlye, Generally of al I will bring two teſtimonies very ſufficient.
<note place="margin">Ep. 42.</note> S. <hi>Auſten</hi> wryting to <hi>Madau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces</hi> that were Idolators: you ſee (ſaith he) that the poteſtates and Peeres of this world them ſelues, that haue bene wonne by the Chriſtians not reſiſting but willingly dyeng, haue turned theyr force and lawes aganſt theſe Idols, for the which before they put Chriſtians to death. <hi>Et Imperii nobiliſſimi culmen emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiſſimum
<pb facs="tcp:2674:15"/>ad ſepulchrum Petri piſcatoris ſubmiſſo diademate ſupplicare: haec omnia ſcripturae diuinae ante longiſſima tempora fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura eſſe teſtata ſunt.</hi> And the moſt lofty toppe of the noble Empyre humbling the ſtately crowne, maketh ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at Peter the fiſhers tombe: all theſe things the diuine ſcriptures witneſſed long before ſhould come to paſſe. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> alſo wryteth thus.
<note place="margin">Homeli. qd. Chriſtus ſit Deus.</note> 
               <hi>Romae quae vrbs eſt regaliſſima &amp;c. At Rome, vvhich is the moſt royall citty, Kinges, Lieutenantes, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, all other things ſet apart runne to the tombes of the Fiſher and the Tent-maker. And in Conſtantinople our Emperours thinke it a great benefite to haue their bodies buryed not hard by the Apoſtles, but at the leaſt vvithout their chappell dore a litle, and notvvithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they vvere Princes of the vvorld, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be dore-keepers to poore fiſhers.</hi> Is not here going, running, kneeling, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, burieng at the Apoſtles memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es? And is not that playne Pilgrimage? Is it not the verye honoring of ſacred R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>likes after the preſent Catholicke
<pb facs="tcp:2674:15"/>maner? Were they all fooles, all aſſes, all ſuperſtitious, all Idolatours? Yea I will ſay with S. Hierome:
<note place="margin">Cont. Vigil. ſcripto. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Did Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne the Emperour commit ſacriledge, vvhen he tranſlated the holy Relikes of Andrevv, Luke, and Timothie to Conſtantinople:
<note place="margin">Great ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in traſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lating or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing of Relikes.</note> before the vvhich Reliks the diuels rore, and confeſſe they feele the preſence of theſe Saynts? Shall vve ſay that Arcadius (Emperour at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) is guiltie of ſacriledge for tranſlatinge Samuels bones ſo longe tyme after his death from Ievvry into Thracia? Are all thoſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops not only ſacrilegious but alſo fooles and aſſes, vvho caried in ſilke and in a golden cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin that vvhich Vigilantius calleth a moſte vyle theng and nothing els but vvynd-blovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſſhes? Are the people of all pariſhes doltes and dyſards, vvho came to meete the boly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks, and receaued them ſo ioyfully, as if they had ſeene the Prophete preſente and alyue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them? in ſo much that from Paleſtine to Calcedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſvvarmes of people vvere cluſtered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſinging vvith one voice to the praiſe of Chriſt.</hi> Here are many goodly poynts to be noted: the vniuerſal practiſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:2674:16"/>Primatiue Church, the principal cauſe and finall ende thereof, the prayſe of Chriſt, Reliks honored becauſe they were the Reliks of <hi>Samuell, Samuell</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored becauſe he was the Prophete of Chriſt, ſo deuoutly &amp; in ſuch ſwarmes becauſe they now ſawe them, and by occaſion thereof entred into a higher conſideration what a maruelous man he was, how farre in God his fauour: borne by miracle of a barren woman, dedicated or vowed to God before he was borne, famylier with him beinge but a child, nerer then of his counſell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Hely</hi> the high prieſt, able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d rayne and to ſtay it, to make Kings and to depoſe them, at one worde a moſte excellent Prophete. Theſe meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I ſay by occaſion of the eye trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the mynd (as <hi>S.
<note place="margin">Cap. 18. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt.</note> Chriſoſtome</hi> and <hi>S. Auſten</hi> ſpeake in the lyke caſes) made them ſo affected toward the Reliks as if they had ſeene the Prophete preſent.
<note place="margin">Cap. 5. de cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra pro mort.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now then to go one ſteppe furder, If to ſee the place onely or ſome bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:2674:16"/>monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, doth ſo much ſtyrre vp de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion (as by theſe former examples appereth) that it iuſtly moued al good folke to trauail vnto them:
<note place="margin">Myracles wrought by Reliks cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</note> which is properly Pilgrimage. When it pleaſed God moreouer to ſhew not onely <hi>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pretioſa in conſpectu Domini mors ſanctorum eius:</hi> How preſious in his ſight the death of his ſaintes is, but alſo <hi>quam mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilis Deus in ſanstis ſuis:</hi> HOW merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a God he is in his ſaynctes, when it pleaſed him I ſay to worke ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, to beſtow his gratious gifts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the poore, the lame, the ſicke, and ſuch like, and that at the tombes, by the verie vertue of his ſaintes Relikes: That, by al reaſon did much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe this deſire, inflame this deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, multiplye Pilgrimes and Pilgrimages. This was it that made the Princes of the earth bowe their crownes to the ſhrynes of the Apoſtles and Martyrs: When they ſaw the deuels rore there, wicked ſpirits caſt out, the blind to ſee the lame to go, the dead to riſe agayne,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:17"/>
               <hi>Ipſi videntes ſic,
<note place="margin">pſal. 47.</note> abmirati ſunt, conturbati ſunt, commoti ſunt, tremor apprehendit eos.</hi> They ſeeyng ſuch wonderful works, were amaſed, aſtonyſhed, apawled, trembled to conſider it, ſayng that that goeth before in the ſame pſalme. <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Dominus &amp; laudabilis nimis:</hi> The lord is great and exceeding prayſe worthy. And agayne:
<note place="margin">For the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</note> 
               <hi>Nimis honorati ſunt amici tui Deus:</hi> Thy frendes O God are become very honorable.</p>
            <p>But doubteſt thou Reader, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euer anye ſuch thinge hath bene done or no? No maruayle in this our faythleſſe age wherein is veryfied the ſaying of our Sauiour:
<note place="margin">Luc. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Putas cum vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit filius hominis, inueniet fidem in terra?</hi> Shall the ſonne of man thinkeſt thou finde any fayth vpon the earth, when he cometh? But thou art a reaſonable man, thou wilte beleeue thoſe that in thyne owne iudgemente are worthye of credit, if they tell it thee. To omit <hi>S. Ambroſe, Chriſoſtome, Hierome,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe teſtymonyes are verye
<pb facs="tcp:2674:17"/>playne and very many: let <hi>S.
<note place="margin">S Auſtens. teſtimonie of ſundrie myracles.</note> Auſten</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in this my breuitie for all the reſte: a man ſo farre from all ſuperſtition as he is from fayning or forginge: from both ſo farre, as the graueſt, wiſeſt, beſt learned Doctor of the Church muſte needs be: Read at thy leaſure the eight chapter of his twentye two booke <hi>de Ciuitate Dei</hi> through out. In the maene tyme I choſe out theſe his wordes for thee to waye indifferently. <hi>Miraculum quod Mediolani factum eſt cum illic eſſemus. The miracle that vvas vvroughte at Millan vvhen vve vvere there,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> at vvhat tyme a blynd man vvas made to ſee, might vvel come to the knovvledge of manye becauſe it is a great cittie, and the Emperour vvas there at the ſame tyme, and the thinge vvas done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a greate concurſe of people to beare vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, that ranne by heapes to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of the Martyrs Geruaſius and Protaſius: vvhich bodies hauing bene longe ſo hid that no man could tell of them,
<note place="margin">Amb. ſer. 91 nameth the man &amp; his occupation</note> vvere founde by a reuelation that Ambroſe the Biſhoppe had in his ſleepe: At the vvhich very place the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:2674:18"/>blynd man vvas deliuered from his olde dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and ſavve the daye lighte.</hi> He telleth moreouer of a yong man ſo horribly poſſeſſed of an euill ſpirite, that he lay for dead, from the which he was dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and reſtored alſo to his eye, that by force of the ſpirite departing from him, hanged downe vpon his cheeke. And this was done at the memory on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that is to ſaye ſome litle Relike of the forſayed Martyrs, farre from <hi>Millan</hi> where the bodyes lye: in <hi>Africke,</hi> at a towne called <hi>Victoriana,</hi> leſſe then thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie myles from <hi>S. Auſtens</hi> biſhoppricke. Note by the waye that of one Martyr there were dyuers memories,
<note place="margin">S. Steuens relikes in ſundrie places.</note> that is, ſome Relike or other of him in ſundry places:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As of <hi>S. Steuen</hi> he reconeth vp ſeuen or eight, at all greate myracles wrought:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> At the one, a blynd woman ſaw, at an other, the Biſhop that caried the Reliks was immediatly healed of a fiſtula:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> at another a Preiſt cured of the ſtone or grauell <hi>per memoriam ſupradicti Martyris:</hi> by the Relike of the forſayed
<pb facs="tcp:2674:18"/>Martyr. Agayne a man of worſhip that was a verye Infidell, made an earneſt Chriſtian by the feruent prayer of his ſonne in lawe <hi>ad memoriam Martyris,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> at the Martyrs Reliks: At another, a yong chylde and a nonne rayſed from death to lyfe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> and many other beſids at other places reuyued whom he there recy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. At length he concludeth thus: <hi>Quid faciam? VVhat ſhall I doe? My promiſe to ende this booke forceth me that I can not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe all vvhich I knovve. And vvithout doubt moſte parte of our countrye men vvhen they ſhall read theſe, vvill be ſory that I haue omitted ſo many thinges vvhich they knovve as vvell as I: of vvhom I craue pardon.
<note place="margin">Myracles in many places by S. Steue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Relikes,</note> For to let paſſe other, if I vvould vvryte the myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous cures onely that haue bene done by this Martyr, to vvit, Steuen that moſte glorious ſaynte, at Calamnes and vvith vs, I mighte make many bookes.</hi> In the ende he telleth at large a wonderfull cure donne vpon one <hi>Paule</hi> and his ſiſter <hi>Palladia</hi> in his owne Church at <hi>S. Steuens</hi> Reliks,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelfe was preſent: <hi>Tam clarum atque
<pb facs="tcp:2674:19"/>illuſtre miraculum, vt nullum arbitrer eſſe Hipponenſium, qui boc non vel viderit vel didicerit: nullum qui obliuiſci vlla ratione potuerit.</hi> So euident and famous a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle (ſayeth he) that I thinke there is none in al Hippo but he ſaw it or hath heard of it, none that can poſſibly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it. His concluſion to ſhut vpp the matter is that which I make the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ground of all theſe Pilgrimages, the honor of Chriſt in his ſayntes. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultabant in Dei laudem voces &amp;c. There vvas ſuch a ſound of their voyces that coulde not ſpeake for ioy, in the prayſe of God, that our eares might hardly abyde it. Quid erat in cordibus exultantium niſi fides Chriſti, pro qua Stephani ſanguis effuſus eſt? VVhat vvas there in their hartes that ſo reioyſed, but the fayth of Chriſt, for the vvhich Steuen ſhed his bloud?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And are there yet Chriſtian men in the worlde that doe diſcredite the mighty power and glorious workes of Chriſt in his ſayntes?
<note place="margin">Agaynſt faythles he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes that diſcredit myracles.</note> Yea (God wot) there are yet <hi>Eunomians</hi> and <hi>Porphirians</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:19"/>that ſaye theſe were but deluſions of noughty ſpirites,
<note place="margin">Hiero. aduc. Vigil.</note> and that they did not rore in very dede, but fained as though they ſuffered intollerable tormentes. Yet there are ſtubburne <hi>Arians</hi> that is to ſay heretickes, who (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth) would in no wyſe confeſſe that the martyrs <hi>Geruaſius</hi> &amp; <hi>Protaſius did</hi> vex the diuels, or make the blynd man ſee:
<note place="margin">Sermo. 91.</note> whereas the ſpirites them ſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed it, and of the man named <hi>Seu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rus</hi> it was a thing famouſly knowen: yet there are Iewiſhe Scrybes that ſaye of Chriſt and his ſaynts: <hi>In nomine Belzebub eiiciunt daemonia: In the name of Belzebub they caſt out diuels.</hi> Yet there are hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall Phariſes that prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as though they gaue all the honor to God, which they detracte from his ſaynts and their Reliks, lyke to the Iewes that ſayed to the blynde man whom Chriſt had cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Da gloriam Deo: Geue God the prayſe</hi> good felow: yea a lamentable caſe to conſider, yet there are among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an men as farre from beleeuing the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb facs="tcp:2674:20"/>done by Sayntes,
<note place="margin">To diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit miracles is plaine pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme.</note> as were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme the Paynims: in ſo much that the learned bookes of <hi>Chryſoſtome, Auſten,</hi> and others made in this caſe to proue agaynſt them, are not ſufficient to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our owne faythleſſe falſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood: wherein I maruaile they are not aſhamed, pretending the name and profeſſion of Chriſtians, agaynſt the authorytye of the wholle Prymytiue Church, to plead the Paynims cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who to diſcredit the miracles of Chriſt and his Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">22. eiuit. c. 8.</note> obiected thus, as <hi>S. Auſten</hi> writeth. <hi>Cur nunc illa miracula quae praedicatis facta eſſe, non fiunt? VVhy are not the lyke myracles donne novv a dayes to them vvhich you ſaye vvere vvrought ſometyme</hi> (by the Apoſtles?) To anſwere them fully (although to alleage later myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles was not neceſſary, becauſe at the beginning they were requiſite til faith was planted, afterwarde they were not to be loked for) yet to anſwere them fully, whereas it pleaſed God alwayes from tyme to tyme to nouriſhe fayth
<pb facs="tcp:2674:20"/>and deuotion by them, theſe holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alleadge myracles wrought at ſayntes tombes, by their Relikes. The paynims were at a poynt to beleeue neither the one nor the other. what doth <hi>Luther?</hi> what <hi>Caluin?</hi> The former they are content to admit, leaſt they ſhold be otherwiſe no chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. The la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they wil not grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t leaſt they ſhould be good Catholiks. But, <hi>S. Auſten</hi> ſaith of both ſorts thus. <hi>Non credu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hoc, qui eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſum per integra virginalia ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris enixum, &amp; ad diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pulos ſuos oſtiis clauſis ingreſſum fuiſſe non credunt.</hi> They do not beleeue theſe later, which alſo do not beleeue that our Lord Ieſus was borne of his mother wythout empayring of her virginitie, and that he entred in to his diſciples, the doores beyng ſhutte:
<note place="margin">The auncy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Doctors did eaſely-beleue my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</note> Againe he ſaieth to philoſophers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the former, that which may verie wel be ſayd to our aduerſaries touching the later.
<note place="margin">Vlt. ciuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei.</note> 
               <hi>Si rem credibilem cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diderunt &amp;c. If chriſtian people did beleeue ſuch thinges as vvere not incredible, let them
<pb facs="tcp:2674:21"/>conſider vvhat fooles they are that do not alſo beleeue it. Agayne if it vvere incredible, hovv is it that al the vvorld hath ſo long beleeued it? S. Hierome</hi> in another caſe of certen mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous faſters, but in the ſame caſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning faythles heretikes, ſaith verie fynely. <hi>Hoc illis incredibile videbitur, qui non credunt omnia poſſibilia eſſe credentibus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n vita Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i Eremitae.</note> This wil ſeme incredible to ſuch as do not beleeue that al thinges are poſſible to them that beleeue. <hi>Nafianzene</hi> alſo that famous doctor wryteth thus. <hi>Et il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud eſt narratu dignum.
<note place="margin">Corin. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vita ſua.</note> That alſo is vvorthy to be toulde, vvhich to many ſeemeth incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as other things doe, ſuch men as thinke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that they ſee done playnely and vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deluſion. My ſelfe dare not diſcredit them, vvhom ſtrang thyngs do moue as much as any man: for in deed it is vvorſe to ſtand ſtyfly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt all thinges vniuerſally, then contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvyſe to be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to beleeue any thing eaſely: this proceedeth of ſimplicitye and lightnes, that of preſumptuous bouldnes.</hi> Fynally the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>Charitas omnia credit.</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie beleeueth al things. which is trew
<pb facs="tcp:2674:21"/>in this ſenſe, that a charitable man is not conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tious and ſelfwilled to ſtand agaynſt the likely report of an honeſt man, much leſſe againſt al ſenſes, al rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, al authority al cuſtome &amp; practiſe. and therfore to ſuch, <hi>S. Auſten</hi> ſheweth alſo the reaſon why it is verie credible that ſaynts do worke theſe myracles at their tombs &amp; Reliks. <hi>Haec a domino im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrare poſſunt propter cuius nomen occiſi ſunt.
<note place="margin">22. ciuit ca. 8, 9. 10.</note> They can eaſely obteyne theſe thinges of our Lord, for vvhoſe names ſake they vvere put to death. Praeceſſit corum mira patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia, vt in bi: miraculis tanta iſta potentia ſequeretur. Their vvo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful patience vvent before, that in theſe myracles this ſo great povver might folovve after. Credamus ergo eis &amp; vera dicentibus &amp; mira facientibus. Dicendo enim vera paſſi ſunt, vt poſſint facere mira.</hi> Let vs therfore beleeue them both when they ſay tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and when they do wonderfully: for by ſayeng trewly they ſuffred death, that they might be able to do wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, <hi>So far S. Auſten.</hi> To conclude this point agaynſt al ſtubbourne negatiues
<pb facs="tcp:2674:22"/>and Ethnyſhe reaſoning, the ſame ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father him ſelfe was ſo eaſie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and ſo careful to publyſh them, becauſe he knew God was much glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in them, that he toke orderin his owne Church where <hi>S. Steuens</hi> Relikes were, to haue al the miracles from tme to time written. <hi>Id namque fieri voluimus, cum videremus antiquis ſimilia diuinarum ſigna virtutum, etiam noſtris temporibus fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentari, &amp; ea non debere multorum noticiae deperire.</hi> For we would haue it ſo, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as we ſaw that, the like ſignes of God his power to them of olde tyme were often ſhewed in our age alſo, to the ende they might not dye but be knowen of manye.</p>
            <p>To ſay the very truth, there are two euident cauſes why the heretikes of our tyme abhorre from this article and others:
<note place="margin">The cauſes of heretical increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of Relikes.</note> Lacke of fayth, and want of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion: ſuch as <hi>S. Iude</hi> diſcribeth in his epiſtle. <hi>Animales, ſpiritum non habentes.</hi> Brutiſh men that haue no feelinge of the ſpirit at all. <hi>Arbores autumnales,</hi> lyke
<pb facs="tcp:2674:22"/>dead trees, when their leafe is ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llen. They litle conſider the power that Chriſt ſo aſſuredly promiſed to his ſayntes. <hi>Amen Amen dico vobis. Verely Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely I ſay vnto you,</hi> he that beleeueth me, the workes that I doe, ſhal he alſo doe, and greater then they are ſhall he be able to doe. They can be as ſtoute as <hi>S. Thomas</hi> to auouche and to ſweare it, that they wyll not beleeue, vnles they put their fingers in the verie print of the nayles. But when the thing is ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident &amp; palpable,
<note place="margin">Heretikes haue no ſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual film of feruen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deuotion.</note> that in deede they may ſee, touch, &amp; handle the glorious myracles wrought at holie places, as it were the marks of martyrs blood, and certen prints of Chriſtes nayles left to vs by the vertue of his paſſion, they are farre from the heauenly affection that <hi>Thomas</hi> felt, when he brake out with hart &amp; voiſe into this goodly confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Dominus meus &amp; Deus meus. My Lord and my God.</hi> O if they did know what it were to touch the memorie onely of Chriſts wounds and his ayntes, what
<pb facs="tcp:2674:23"/>it were to adore but in the place where his feete ſtoode, to ſitte at his feete a whyle with <hi>Mary</hi> and waſhe them with weepinge teares: to touch the hemme onely of his garment and feele the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that proceadeth from thence, to ſee but a glimſe of his glory and his ſaynts with the three Apoſtles, and in all this to heare as it were this voyce of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> vnto <hi>Peter, Dominus eſt,</hi> It is our Lorde, it is he that maketh the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils rore, he healeth the ſicke, he ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the dead, becauſe his ſaynts doe it by him, his preſence and power is in all theſe thinges: then vndoubtedly they would take Peters fayth and nothing doubt ſafely to tread vpon the ſeas and waues of infidelitie: they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue his ineſtimable ioy, ſaying: <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt nobis hic eſſe.</hi> O this is a ſweete place, well were we if we might tarry here:
<note place="margin">The won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion of chatholiks.</note> let vs make here tabernacles, to thee O Lord firſt, and next to thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſayntes. This fayth and affection had <hi>Paula,</hi> when ſhe came to the place
<pb facs="tcp:2674:23"/>in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> where Chriſt was borne, ſaying: here is my reſtinge place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is my Lords country: here wil I dwell, becauſe our Sauiour hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen it: and agayne when in her letters to <hi>Marcella</hi> which <hi>S. Hierome</hi> penned. <hi>Shall it euer be our good happe to ſee the day, vvhen vve maye goe together into the litle vaulte, vvhere our Sauiour vvas borne? To vveepe a litle in our Lords ſepulcher, to licke the vvood of the holy Croſſe, and in Mount-oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet vvith vvill and vviſh to aſcende after a ſorte vvith our Lord, as if he vvere very novv aſcending? To ſee Lazarus come furth tyed in his vvynding ſheete? Amos the prophet euen yet playing on his bag-pype vpon ſome litle hillocke? aftervvard in Samaria to honour the aſhes of Iohn Baptiſt, Heliſeus and Abdias, all three together?</hi> This deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> to <hi>Paules</hi> cheynes, the people of the Eaſte parts to <hi>Samuels</hi> Reliks: the beſte men out of all places to the holy land, as before I haue mentioned. This made bleſſed <hi>Anthony</hi> to goe a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous iourney to <hi>Paule</hi> the wonderfull
<pb facs="tcp:2674:24"/>Eremite of whom he reported to his ſcholers thus: <hi>I haue ſeene (I tell you) Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a pauli.</note> I haue ſeene Iohn in the vvildernes, and to ſay truely, I haue ſeene Paule in Paradyſe.</hi> This deuotion was it that made <hi>Hilari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to doe the lyke toward <hi>S.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iero. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a Hilario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is.</note> Antony</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death: in whoſe litle cabbin he layed him downe, and as though he had felte it warme as yet of the holy man departed, ſo he culled and kiſſed it: This was it that cauſed the godlye contention betweene the <hi>Paleſtines</hi> and them of <hi>Cypres</hi> aboute the ſelfe ſame wonderfull man <hi>Hilarion,</hi> who after his death in both places wrought greate miracles, but eſpecially in <hi>Cypres,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke (ſayeth <hi>S. Hierome</hi>) becauſe he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that place beſt.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2. Ciuit. 3.</note> This deuotion and this fayth was it that worked in thoſe <hi>Africanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouch of relikes.</note> which <hi>S. Auſten</hi> wryteth of, when they touched three dead perſons with the garmentes, and anoynted the body of an other with the oyle that had touched onely S. <hi>Steuens</hi> Reliks, &amp; immediatly all fower were reuyued.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:24"/>
            <p>Where marke for your comforte and ioy al you good religious and wel diſpoſed perſons that carry Croſſe or beades,
<note place="margin">The lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſſer thinges then relike</note> hauing touched glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, the better to put you in mynd of ſuch ſayntes and to pray the more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly (for to that purpoſe I would haue it employed.) Marke I ſay how exceedinglye ſuch deuotion pleaſeth God, wheras he confirmed it ſo long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe by myracles. And no maruaile, for he is the ſame good Lorde ſtill, that ſtreight perceaued the feruente fayth of the pore woman, that thought it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, with great feare and reuerence to touch but the hemme of his garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. He that by <hi>Peters</hi> ſhadowe and <hi>Paules</hi> clothes healed the ſicke and cured the lame, muſt now alſo needs accepte all deuotion donne towarde him and his ſayntes for his ſake: he can not choſe, becauſe he is alwayes lyke him ſelfe: <hi>Fidelis eſt, ſeipſum negare non poteſt.</hi> You al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that delight to haue <hi>Agnoſ-Dei, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalias, Graynes</hi> or the lyke honorable
<pb facs="tcp:2674:25"/>memories of heauenly thinges and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlamers of deuotion, ſuch I ſay as the holy hande of Chriſts high Vicar hath bleſſed for that intent, geue God harty thankes for your religious mynde, if you feele in deede that it proceede of deuotion. It is not geuen to euerye man although he would, to haue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſmall thinges no ſmall deuotion. Smal things in compariſon, otherwyſe not ſmall that haue greate commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.
<note place="margin">Litle halo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed tokens ſent from<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Byſhoppes as appereth in their epiſtles.</note> The learned Fathers and holye men of auncient tyme, <hi>Auſten, Paulinus, Leo, Gregory,</hi> here alſo haue geuen you example: who although by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent knowledge of ſcriptures they vnderſtoode all diuine miſteries and thereby were inflamed to loue Chriſt exceedingly, yet they gladly vſed to practyſe their deuotion by theſe leſſer meanes alſo,
<note place="margin">Leo. ep. 72.</note> ſending one to the other <hi>panes benedictos, imagunculas, particulas ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae ſanctae, particulam Dominicae Crucis cum culogiis,</hi> halowed bread, litle images of Chriſt, our Ladye, and the Apoſtles:
<pb facs="tcp:2674:25"/>ſome portion of the holy lande, and as <hi>Leo</hi> ſpeaketh a litle peece of our Lords Croſſe with bleſſings adioyned. <hi>S.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Li.</hi> 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y. 60.</note> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> in an epiſtle to <hi>Edelbertus</hi> Kinge of our country hath theſe wordes. <hi>Parua autem xenia tranſiniſi, quae vobis non crunt parua, cum a vobis ex beati Petri Apoſtoli be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictione fuerint ſuſcepta.</hi> I haue ſent you certen ſmall tokens, which ſhall not be of ſmall valew to you, when you haue receaued them as hauing the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>S. Peter</hi> the Apoſtle. Wherby he meaneth that the gratious bleſſing of <hi>Peter</hi> the firſte Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſtill in al his Succeſſours to bleſſe and ſanctifie ſacred tokens: So that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> his bleſſing is the very bleſſing of <hi>S. Peter</hi> him ſelfe, euen as in other caſes alſo the whole Councell of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> proteſted: <hi>Petrus per Leonem locutus eſt:</hi> Peter him ſelfe hath ſpoken by the mouth of Leo. It is a very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon phraſe or ſpeach in <hi>S. Gregory</hi> that he ſendeth <hi>S. Peters</hi> bleſſinge when he ſendeth litle golden keyes or croſſes
<pb facs="tcp:2674:26"/>that had touched his bodye, to noble men, to Princes, to the Empereſſe, to Biſhops in all countries, wherin ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme to make the gifte more pretious he put a litle of the holy Croſſe, of <hi>S. Peters</hi> cheyne, of <hi>S. Iohn Baptiſts</hi> heare, of <hi>S. Laurence</hi> gridyron: which the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed partyes did weare aboute their neckes for moſt holy and ſacred rew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,
<note place="margin">Li. 2. cp. 72. 86. li. 3. cp. 30, li. 5. cp. 6. li. 7. epiſt. 126. ind. 2.</note> full of ſpirituall grace and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſinge.</p>
            <p>Men of comon ſenſe and colder feeling in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (if they be catholiks) are moued with the reuerence of ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſacrifiſe, and great ſolemnities, but the morefe ruent a man is and as it were the more famylier With Chriſt, the ſoner he eſpyeth him if he doe ſee but his ſhadow, and ſayth with <hi>S. Iohn, Dominus eſt,</hi> it is our Lord: which other thincke to be <hi>pbantaſma,</hi> an imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onely and darke appearance of ſome tryfling thing. <hi>S, Antbony,</hi> a man of ſo deepe contemplation that he deſyred no other booke to know the infinite
<pb facs="tcp:2674:26"/>wyſdome and mercie of God, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſighte of his goodly creatures, ſawe ſo farre in the very cote of <hi>Paule</hi> the Eremite aboue-named,
<note place="margin">Hiero. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Pauli.</note> which that good man himſelfe had made of palme leaues, that he kepte it for a Relike of that faint, and ware it onely vpon high feaſts in honor of the day. <hi>S. Hierome</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the ende of <hi>Paules</hi> lyfe which he writeth, is wonderfully moued to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with theſe wordes. I humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt euery one that readeth this ſtory to remember <hi>Hierome</hi> the ſinner, who if he mighte haue his wiſhe of God, would much more deſire <hi>Paules</hi> cote with all his good merits, then Princes purple with their painfull puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. And becauſe we talke of holye mens garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,
<note place="margin">Socea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. 7. ca. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the yonger a Prince of noble vertues and verye religious was wont to weare the facke cloth of a certen holy Biſhop that died at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople <hi>quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uis ſordidatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> although it were not very cleane, <hi>perſuaſus ſe ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ex mortui ſanctimonia inde perceptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:27"/>Beinge fullye perſwaded that he ſhould receaue thereof ſomewhat of the dead mans holines. But to returne backe a litle to ſuch men as Chriſten. dome eſteemeth for renowmed Saints: Bleſſed <hi>Hillarion</hi> going in Pilgrimage to S. <hi>Authonies</hi> eremitage,
<note place="margin">Hicro. invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Hilario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> reioyſed in his ſpirit at euery litle memory of that holy man, when it was tould him, here he was wonte to ſing, here to pray, in this place he did worke, and there he reſted him ſelfe, theſe vynes and litle ſtocks were of his planting, that alley he made with his owne handes, this poole coſt him much labour &amp; paynes to water the garden, this mattocke he had manye yeares to digge and delue withall. If this good man be therefore thought a ſuperſtitious foole, becauſe he was a monke forſoth almoſt twelue hundred yeres agoe, and a myracle of that age. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> an Archbiſhop and honorable in the world, was no foole vndoubtedly, howe ſo euer he maye ſeeme ſuperſtitious becauſe he is a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke:
<pb facs="tcp:2674:27"/>He expreſſeth the very lyke affection to the leaſt monumentes of the Apoſtles that you can deuyſe.
<note place="margin">Praefat. in cp. Pauli ad. philemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> 
               <hi>Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>non defuiſſent &amp;c. I vvould there had bene ſome one that could haue geuen vs the vvhole ſtory of the Apoſtles, not onely vvhat they vvrote, but vvhat and vvhen they did eate, vvhere they ſate, vvhither they vvent, and ſo furth. For if vve ſee but the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces onely vvhere they ſate, thither vve direct our mynd oftentymes, and beginne to a vvake, and feele our ſelues better diſpoſed.</hi> And that you may knowe he was alwayes the ſame man, tender harted toward all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred monuments were they neuer ſo litle,
<note place="margin">See. qd vtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti ſit v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</note> he wryteth of him ſelfe that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a picture in wax, wherein the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell deſtroyed ſo many thouſand Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians in one night, as in the booke of Kinges is mentioned, he was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully delighted to behold the mighty power of God in that ſmall image of ſory wax. All the which examples doe declare this one point what grace they had and how vertuous men they were
<pb facs="tcp:2674:28"/>that of ſmall thinges could reape great deuotion,
<note place="margin">Prophane affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſee u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler monu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes.</note> deuotion I ſay toward God and his ſayntes, not as prophane here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiks that more gladly looke vpon <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> face becauſe he was eloquente, or <hi>Caluins</hi> rounde cappe becauſe he was a miniſter, or ſome noble mans armes, that is Patrone of their biſhopricke. No no, but the ſweete picture of ſome heauenly thinge, the bleſſing of a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous hand or of Gods anoynted, the vew of holy place, and touch of ſacred Relike, theſe worke wonderfully the prayſe of God in the hartes of ſad and ſober Chriſtians.
<note place="margin">22. ciuit. 8.</note> S. <hi>Auſten</hi> noteth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye diligently in him that prayed inſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly at S. <hi>Steuens</hi> memory for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law that was a Panyme and lay very ſicke, how he tooke away with him of the flowers that were vpon the Altar, ſuch as came firſt to hand, which in the nighte he putte vnder the ſicke mans head, and before day he cryeth out in all haſte to ſende for the Biſhop, and ſo was baptyſed and not long after
<pb facs="tcp:2674:28"/>made a godly end. Of another he wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that had the palſye, who requeſted to be brought to a new chappel that was built a litle before by S <hi>Auſtens</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ouer a portion of that holy land wher Chriſt roſe agayne, for the more reuerent reſeruing therof, thyther he was brought and imediatly recouered. Agayne, I know (ſaith he) a mayd of <hi>Hippo</hi> this cittie, who anoynting her ſelfe with oyle embrewed with the teares of a preiſt that prayed for her, was deliuered from an euill ſpirite. S. <hi>Hierome</hi> wryteth of the aboue-named <hi>Hilarion</hi> that Biſhoppes, preiſts, iudges, men of great calling, graue and welthy matrones, beſides the common people out of country and towne, tanne to him in heapes onely to take halowed bread and oyle at his handes:
<note place="margin">Halowed bread and oyle.</note> which had the vertue to preſerue from death, namely the doughter of one <hi>Conſtance</hi> and her huſbande. All theſe thinges being practiſed by men of ſuch vertue and reported to vs by doctours of ſo
<note place="margin">Agaynſt ſcoffing he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:29"/>great authoritie, ſkoffyng heretickes wil ieſt at: and no maruel. The prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of <hi>Inde</hi> the Apoſtle can not be falſe. <hi>In nouiſſimo tempore venient illuſores, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum deſideria ſua ambulantes in impietati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> In the later tyme ther ſhall come mockers, walkyng at their pleaſure in all vngodlines. Such were the yong laddes, <hi>irrifores</hi> as, S. <hi>Auſten</hi> calleth them that laughed the poore olde man <hi>Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> to ſkorne for prayeng at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks of the twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty martyrs,
<note place="margin">22 ciuit. 8.</note> that he might by ſome meanes haue wherewith to cloth him, which he obtened as there is told very myraculoſly. Such were they that ieſted at <hi>Macarius</hi> the Byſhoppe of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sozom. li. 2. Cap. 1.</note> when they ſaw him put two of the croſſes to the ſycke woman and that ſhe Was nothing the better, and thought it a verie foolyſhe moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery: who were controwled by and by with the third croſſe, that healed her, bycauſe it was the ſame croſſe that our Sauiour ſuffered on, as appered by the myracle. <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:2674:29"/>he was ſometime in theſe caſes very incredulous,
<note place="margin">Niceph. li. 18. ca. 31.</note> yet ſuch a ſkoffer he was not: who thought at the firſt that the myracles done at <hi>Euphonia</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs ſhryne were deluſions wroughte by men, but he tryed the contrary by ſuch vnfallible meanes that euer after he honored them exceedingly.
<note place="margin">Hiero.</note> But <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantius</hi> was an ould captayne of ſuch ſcoffing mates, who called the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks, aſhmongers: Reliks, foliſh duſte wrapped in a clowte: wax candles bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before them, vyle taper lighte. Such were <hi>Eunomius</hi> and <hi>Porphyrius</hi> that ſayed the diuels made as though they had bene formented greeuouſlye by martyrs Relikes, whereas they felte no ſuch thing.
<note place="margin">Marc. 5.</note> Such were they that laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Chriſt him ſelfe: <hi>Irridebant eum</hi> (ſayeth the Euangeliſt) when he ſayed of <hi>Iairus</hi> doughter, <hi>Puella non eſtmortuae, ſed dormit.</hi> The mayed ie not dead but ſleepeth. And vndoubtedly theſe ieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of our tyme, if very ſhame of the world rather then feare of hell did not
<pb facs="tcp:2674:30"/>ſtay them, would laugh merely at <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſhadow,
<note place="margin">Act. 5. Iac. 5. Io. 9 Tob. 9. Dan. 14 Iud. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. Reg. 2</note> 
               <hi>Iames</hi> oyle, <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſpittle, <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phaels</hi> fiſhe, <hi>Daniel</hi> dragon, <hi>Samſons</hi> law-bone, and <hi>Elias</hi> cloke. Doeſt thou wonder why I will ſay ſo, and tell me that I ought not to iudge? Becauſe it is euidente they can neither abyde ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, nor beleeue myracle, it is their profeſſion. For example, <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in the diſputations at <hi>Oxford</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vrged in the queſtion of the bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sacrament with this axample,
<note place="margin">Peter mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſtes miracle en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring when the doores was ſhutt.</note> that Chriſt entred into the place where his diſciples were, the dores being ſhutte, ſayed that he firſt opened the dore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoth, and ſo entred: A wonderfull my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle that Chriſt did goe in when the dore ſtood open. As well he might ſay that he could not haue ryſen agayne vnleſſe the Angell had firſte remoued the ſtone from the ſepulcher, nor be borne of his mother without breache of her virginitie, which infidelitie <hi>S. Auſten</hi> obiecteth to the Paynims as I haue before mentioned. But eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2674:30"/>in the facte of <hi>Eliſeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Reg. 6.</note> when he caſte a pyce of wood into the water to make the yron ſwimme that before did ſinke appeareth what they would do if they durſt: which when a witty catholicke to confound a ſcoffing hereticke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him barely without cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of <hi>Eliſeus</hi> or of ſcripture,
<note place="margin">A ſkoffing heretike finely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</note> as though ſome monke had wryten it, aſking his iudgment, if it were not like to the fooliſh fables of Papiſts concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning miracles at martyrs tombes: This good felow by his wiſdome made gay ſport with it, till he vnderſtood it was playne ſcripture, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in what plight he was you may eaſely gheſſe, in his owne play to be ſo flatly foyled. So li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle they vnderſtand the wiſdome and power of God,
<note place="margin">Myracles as truly wro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, as ſometyme by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</note> who of purpoſe hath choſen by ſmall and foliſh thinges (as they may ſeeme) to confound and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trowle the hawty witts of worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners.</p>
            <p>If they will tell me that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſcripture reporteth, the authority
<pb facs="tcp:2674:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:32"/>therof forceth them to beleeue it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though reſon reclayme: but for all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther teſtimonies, it is at their pleaſure to beleeue them or not: <hi>S. Auſten</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth,
<note place="margin">22. ciuit. 8.</note> that for the truth of thinges: <hi>Etiam nunc fiunt miracula in eius nomine, ſiue per ſacramenta eius, ſiue per orationes vel memorias ſanctorum.</hi> Nowe alſo at this preſent myracles are wroughte in his name what by his ſacacraments, what by the prayers or memories of ſayntes. But the difference is: <hi>Non eadem claritate illuſtrantur, vt quanta illa gloria diffamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> They are not ſo famouſly knowen not bruted abrode ſo gloriouſly as the other: the reaſon whereof is there alſo to be ſeene moſte reaſonable. If they had rather cauill thus, that <hi>ſignae ſunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelibus,</hi> the myracles that Chriſt and his Apoſtles did, were for vnbeleeuers to bring them to the ſayth: now ſince all the world beleeueth, they are to no purpoſe,
<note place="margin">Aduerſ. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantium.</note> &amp; therfore they thinke there is no ſuch thing. Firſte <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſhall anſwere them &amp; <hi>Vigilantius</hi> all at once,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:32"/>that the queſtion is not betweene vs, for whom they are wrought, but by what power, and therefore <hi>tell me not</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>that vvonders are for ſuch as vvill not beleeue, but anſvvere me bovv in duſt and aſhes there is ſuch a forcible preſence of vvonderfull operations.</hi> Secondly I add moreouer, that becauſe there are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the worlde infidels or vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing heretiks, myracles are alwayes to good purpoſe agaynſt both ſorts, to maintayne true fayth in the hartes of Catholicke Chriſtians, <hi>eodem Deo</hi> (as <hi>S. Auſten</hi> ſayeth) <hi>nunc faciente per quos vult &amp; quemadmodum vult,
<note place="margin">22. ciuit. 8.</note> qui &amp; illa quae legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus fecit.</hi> The ſelfe ſame God working now by whom he will and as he will, that wrought thoſe former which we reade of in ſcriptures.
<note place="margin">Of abuſes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If they will tell me ſadly and rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly that their be many abuſes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, deluſions eſteemed for myracles, falſe reliks, much ſuperſtition. Firſt it is great raſhnes to thinke ſo without euident cauſes as in the notable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:2674:33"/>of <hi>Meuritius</hi> the Emperour before is declared. Agayne, the lyke abuſes haue bene in all ages euen of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, without any preiudice to the Catholike cuſtomes, but to the better tryall of conſtante Chriſtians, which will not ſtumble at euery ſtraw, and refuſe the corne becauſe of the chaffe:
<note place="margin">Adue. vigil.</note> 
               <hi>Paucorum culpa</hi> (ſayeth S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome) <hi>non praeiudicat religioni.</hi> The faulte of a few is no preiudice agaynſt religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Iudas treaſon did not deſtroy the Apoſtles fayth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. ad Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> And agayne: <hi>In omni conditione &amp; gradu optimis mixta ſunt peſſima.</hi> In all ſtats and degrees the worſt things are ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the beſt: which conſideration of former tymes (which by all reaſon ſhoulde be moſte pure the neerer to Chriſt) and that our Sauiour ſayed. <hi>Neceſſe eſt vt veniant ſcandala.</hi> It is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that offences do come, ſeemeth to me a verye goodly inſtruction for weakelings that quickly condemne a good thing, when they ſee it abuſed, of one ſuperſtitious woman iudge all I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatours,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:33"/>for one falſe relike thinke none true,
<note place="margin">S. Gregorie in this caſe put trew Relikes in Place of the falſe, maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholtke vſe redreſſing the abuſe, in his anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatorie of S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</note> for one fayned myracle will geue credit to none. Where of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and holy Martyr of our country <hi>S. Thomas Moore</hi> hath moſte wyſely and pithely (as his maner is) diſputed in his engliſh volumes, ſufficient to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any reaſonable and graue witte. <hi>S. Auſten</hi> wryteth of certen idle monkes or rather falſe monkes in that weede, that went gadding abrode out of their cloyſter ſhewing martyrs reliks (<hi>ſi ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men martyrum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De. op. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. ca. 28.</note> if happely they were ſo in deede) for to gayne by it or to ſeeme the more holy: And yet I trow no man will ſay that he condemneth monkes or reliks, that ſhall reade the ſelfe ſame booke <hi>de opere monachorum,</hi> how monks ought to be occupied, and my former teſtimonyes out of him for myracles. <hi>S. Hierome</hi> telleth of ſome ſuperſtitious wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that caried croſſes about them: whereupon ſome haſtie hereticke will take me ſhort, and by &amp; by conclude, ergo <hi>S. Hierome</hi> doth miſlyke of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:2674:34"/>Croſſes: Let him ſtaye his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for he addeth alſo, <hi>&amp; parua euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelia,</hi> and ſhe caried alſo the Ghoſpell in a litle volume: did that alſo miſlyke <hi>S. Hierome</hi> trow you? No ſoothly, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one nor the other well vſed, and as well the one as the other abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<note place="margin">Hiero. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantiae ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouae.</note> if they beare them to ſeeme the more holy, as the Phariſees did their ten commaundementes in the brode hemme of their garments, and therfore are checked of our Sauiour. It would requyre a iuſte volume to reckon the enormities crepte in among religious tytes and cuſtomes, in all ages ſince the aſcenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, and as the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſtians multiplyed, ſo (as it happeneth in a multitude) the more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſes: whereof the aunciente Fathers make often mention and lament it.
<note place="margin">Ad. Ruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mona.</note> As when <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſayeth: <hi>Vidimus nuper &amp; planximus:</hi> we hane ſeene of late and it greeued vs not a litle. And agyne, <hi>piget dicere:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Euſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium.</note> I am loth to tell how many vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins dayly fall from their porpoſe and
<pb facs="tcp:2674:34"/>profeſſion: And agayne,
<note place="margin">Ad Sauin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diaco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</note> 
               <hi>prorumpunt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimae antequam verba.</hi> O villanie, I can more eaſelye weepe in this caſe then ſpeake. Of all the which things, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the vnprofitable ceremonyes and ſuperfluous deuotion, which are the priuate fanſies of vnſkilfull perſons, not the publicke ordinances and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Church, the firſt Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> and after it <hi>S.
<note place="margin">Ep. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Auſten</hi> geueth this generall rule, which at all tyme taketh place and is our warrantyſe: what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is agaynſt fayth or good lyfe that the Church of God <hi>nec approbat, nec ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, nec facit:</hi> doth neither allow, nor diſſemble, nor put in practyſe. And this much mighte well be anſwered if happely there be any ſinfull abuſes at this day. Firſt that we can not be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Primatiue Church, which in all points had the like, as I wil ſhew if it be needefull. Secondly all good Catholicks that ſee any ſuch faultes, much more lamente them then the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticke doth blame them, the more it
<pb facs="tcp:2674:35"/>greeueth them that by ſuch offences the truth is ill ſpoken of among our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies, and ſuſpected of them that are indifferent to both. Thirdly, the words of our Sauiour muſt needs be fulfilled, <hi>Neceſſe eſt vt veniant ſcandala.</hi> Offences muſt neceſſarely come, there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, ſuch is the ſinfull frayletie of mans nature.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> But <hi>Pax multa diligentions eum, &amp; non eſt illis ſcandalum:</hi> They are at greate peace which loue him, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can offende them or make them to fall from the truth. Loue Chriſt and his Catholicke Church as thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt doe, and no abuſe be it neuer ſo greate ſhall be able to moue thee one iotte from the pure profeſſion of all laudable cuſtomes.</p>
            <p>Howbeit to ſay truly,
<note place="margin">Of ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo called.</note> I thinke he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie hath partly ſo extinguiſhed and partly ſo cooled the feruent deuotion of ryght good earneſt Catholicks, that if there be any religious zeale lefte in ſome few more then in others (which therefore ſeemeth ſuperſtition becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:2674:35"/>it is rare and ſinguler) the ſame is ſo farre from heynous crime or greeuous fault,
<note place="margin">Adue, vigil.</note> that I may compare it rather with their deuotion which in <hi>S. Hieroms</hi> time lyghted tapers at the Ghoſpell tyme, and burned wax candels before Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs tombes, of whom he geueth ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that ech one had rewarde accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they were deuoutly diſpoſed: or with their perſuaſion that at the ſame tyme alſo were wont to ſhew Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims comming to <hi>Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in matth</note> the paue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church as yet imbrewed with <hi>Zacharias</hi> bloud as it was thought, and therefore viſited not without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence: which their godly affection (albeit they were poſſibly deceaued) <hi>S. Hierome</hi> did not miſlyke, toward that glorious Martyr, whoſe death was ſo pretious in Gods ſight, that it was one cauſe of the Iewes extreme deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as our Sauiour himſelfe witneſſeth. So lykewyſe it maye fortune that in ſome Churches or Chappels there is propoſed ſome falſe relike,
<note place="margin">Of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful relikes.</note> and ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored
<pb facs="tcp:2674:36"/>as the relike of that ſaynt whoſe it is not: which thinge if it were done raſhly vpon light credit, and if it might eaſely be diſcerned, were a faulte in no wyſe to be ſuffered: but be cauſe it hath from tyme to tyme bene eſteemed ſo, nothing knowen to the contrary, not diſalowed of the Biſhop (whoſe dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in examining ſuch thinges is to be wiſhed, and in <hi>Fiſher</hi> Biſhoppe and Martyr of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> is greatly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) and eſpecially becauſe the honor reſteth not in the Relike, but is wholy referred to that ſaynt whoſe Relike it is eſteemed: For theſe cauſes I ſay their is no more feare of ſuperſtition or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry in this caſe,
<note place="margin">Mare. 10.</note> then if <hi>Bartimens</hi> the blinde man (in the Ghoſpell) had ſayed to anye other man in ſteede of Chriſt, <hi>Miſertre mei fili Dauid,</hi> Sonne of Dauid haue mercye vppon me: as he might quickly haue done being blind, if they had mocked him and ſhewed an other for Chriſt. Or if a Catholicke ſhould adore that hoſte which a preiſt
<pb facs="tcp:2674:36"/>at the tyme of eleuation lifteth vp not conſecrated, or worſhippe one of the theeues croſſes for the Croſſe of our redemption, if one ſodenly were chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the other: In all theſe caſes and the lyke, ignorance doth excuſe, being neither raſhe nor wilfull: and ſincere meaning hath rewarde before him that knoweth the harte of the worſhipper, that he honoreth vndoutedly the pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall it ſelfe in heauen, howſoeuer he be deceaued agaynſt his will in miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome earthly monumente or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance therof. For example, thou meaneſt to honour the Kings Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as if he were the King him ſelfe: among a number thou doeſt not know him: it is tould thee ſadly that it is he that weareth the gay cote, perhaps he is of his meaneſt gentlemen, yet no doubt thou haſt done thy dutifull obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſance to thy Lorde and Prince, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou be deceaued in this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or that, which is ſayed to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him. How be it in ſacred thinges
<pb facs="tcp:2674:37"/>more heede is to be taken and greater diſcretion to be vſed.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.</note> 
               <hi>Honor Regis iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium diligit:</hi> In honoring the Kinge of Kings and his ſeruants there is much iudgement required.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.</note> We are commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſing to our Lord, but <hi>ſapienter,</hi> wyſely:
<note place="margin">150.</note> and in an other pſalme, <hi>in cim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balis bene ſonantibus,</hi> vpon well ſounding cymbals: They ſound well when eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtring is in tune without diſcorde, neither to high nor to lowe, but in a golden meane, which all good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks in all poyntes of religion moſt hartely wiſh and pray for,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.</note> 
               <hi>vt is qui ex ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſo eſt, vereatur, nihil habens malum dicere de nobis:</hi> That the aduerſary may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed to open his mouth agaynſt vs, when he is able to ſay no euill of vs.</p>
            <p>Thus I haue breifly touched certen poynts concerning Relikes and pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: the name, the cauſe &amp; the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the fruite, the myracles, the vſe and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe, which may be an <hi>interim</hi> to thee Chriſtian Reder agaynſt the odious termes of Idolatrye and ſuperſtition,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:37"/>deuyſed by heretikes as buggiſhe bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to feare babyes. A full diſcourſe of this matter I reſerue as not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, if after theſe fewe the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie be quyet: if not, then I meane God willing to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cke. And to ſhew ſuch a glorious ſight of vniuerſall practiſe and infallible teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, ſo cleare as none dayes. that the beſt of our aduerſaries ſhal be no more able to looke aganſt it although he take <hi>Caluins</hi> ſpectacles, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the owle or the baſtard-egle agaynſt the ſunne beames: not becauſe I can doe much or any thing at all of my ſelf, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſtud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent of catholike diuines, but becauſe it is very much to haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of them that can doe exceading much if they were in place, how much the catholike Church is able to aledge as for al the reſt, ſo for this article alſo. That church, wherof the pſalme ſayth: <hi>Gyorioſa dicta ſunt dete ciuitas dei.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 86.</note> Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things are reported of thee O citty of God: agaynſt that ſynagoge, of the
<pb facs="tcp:2674:38"/>which is ſayd:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſalm. 136.</note> 
               <hi>Filia Babilonis miſera,</hi> the daghter of Babylon is a wreched one. <hi>Bleſſed is he that taketh her vngratious chil, dren</hi> (al heretikes and ſciſmatikes) <hi>and ſquiſeth them aganſt the Rock.</hi> which is the preſent fayth of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> by that commiſſion which Chriſt gaue to <hi>Peter,</hi> whom he made a rocke and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom he built his Church, to whom he promiſed it ſhould not fayle,
<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.</note> and hath performed his promiſe vntill this day. To whom for his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent gifte and our aſſured ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, as many as ſtande vpon this Rocke, be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory for euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:38"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:39"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:39"/>
            <head>A LETTER SENTE BY M. LICENTIATE MARTIN TO A MARIED prieſt his frende.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE M. N. beinge al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies myndful of your cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie toward me, I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thought howe I might beſte requite it; and becauſe I neither haue temporal abilitie, nor you (God be thanked) haue neede therof, I haue purpoſed many times to communicat with you ſome ſpirituall benifite that mighte be to the health of your ſoule. And hauinge differred hitherto, this I truſte is that good houre which God hath appointed me to tel you, and you patiently and willinglye to heare that, which, if you wel conſider, is the moſt neceſſarie thing for you of all other, if you be ſuch a one (as I hope you are) that looke to be ſaued.</p>
            <p>To be ſhorte and to come to the pointe: you haue bene a prieſt manye yeres, your ſelfe for many yeres toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neuer imagined that you mighte
<pb facs="tcp:2674:40"/>marrie, no more then any other prieſt made in the like ſorte as you were. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde the libertie of the time and the ſenſualitie of the fleſhe and onlye worldly conſiderations pricking you forward, and no good or godly reaſon (as your owne conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce can tel you) your fancie fel vpon a woman, and to accompliſhe your deſire, you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how gladly you woulde haue had ſome authoritie of ſcripture or doctor to haue ſoothed you in your fleſhlye purpoſe; and when it was tolde you that there was nothing for it, but all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, you thought or rather you ſayed ſo (for you could not thinke it) that you neuer vowed, and ſo you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to flatter your ſelfe: and when that alſo was ſhewed vnto you and proued cleane contrarie, becauſe all that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them ſelues to a catholike biſhop for orders of ſubdeacon and ſo forth, by their verie preſentation and taking of the orders (although no more were ſaied) do make their vow before God,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:40"/>becauſe the Church alwaies preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that, and admitteth none but with vow, this I ſay ſtanding ſo, you wente farder, and hoped the Counſell of <hi>Tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> would releaſe the vow, or that by your frendes you at the leaſt might obteine a diſpenſation: whereby you declared that your ſelfe thought it not lawfull without diſpenſation, and howe you could once thinke of a diſpenſation, I doe maruell much, wheras there is no example thereof in any priuate mans caſe, ſuch as yours is.</p>
            <p>But when all theſe means failed, yet the deuil blew the coles of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence ſtill, ſpite of the Church, of your vow, of holy and chaſt prieſthod, to match your ſelfe with a woman, not in matrimonie (for you wot wel it can be none) but in damnable ſacrilege worſe then any adulterie, as S. Auſten telleth you, if it woulde pleaſe you to reade it, ſaing of ſuch as haue vowed, <hi>Talibus non ſolum nubere,
<note place="margin">De bono vid. ca. 9. tom. 4.</note> ſed velle nubere damnabile eſt. To ſuch it is damnable, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2674:41"/>to mary, but to haue the vvil to mary.</hi> And this he ſaith vpon S. Pauls authoritie, who writinge of widowes that had vowed and would afterwarde marrie, ſaith:
<note place="margin">8. Tim. 5</note> 
               <hi>Cum luxuriatae fuerint in Chriſto, nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere volunt: habentes damnationem, quia pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam fidem irritam fecerunt. For vvhen they ſhall be vvanton in Chriſt, they vvill marie: hauing damnation, becauſe they haue made voyde their firſt ſayth.</hi> They are damned, becauſe they haue broken their firſte promis, and they brake their firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, becauſe they would marie: ſo that their firſte promis was as yours alſo was, not to marrie.</p>
            <p>And therefore S. Auſten ſaith bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in an other place,
<note place="margin">Eodem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that ſuch mariages are not onely adulteryes, but worſe then any adulterie. And beleeue me M. N. as your verie frend that doe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tender your ſoule toward Chriſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feede your carnal humour toward the world, beleeue me I ſay, that if <hi>S. Ambroſe, S. Auſten, S. Chriſoſtome, S. Baſill, S. Gregorie Nazianzene, S. Ierom, S. Gregory
<pb facs="tcp:2674:41"/>the great, S. Bernard,</hi> or any other aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and learned Doctor were aliue to tel you, they would plainly ſay as now their bookes doe ſay, that your ſtate is damnable. And what if you did but aſke your olde maiſter and Lorde the laſt true biſhopp of Lichefilde, would you not beleeue him, and ſo manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learned and vertuous prelates of theſe our dayes? Shall fleſhe and bloud ouerrule you to doe againſt your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and to your exceeding ſhame before all your frends and al the good chriſtians of the world? Shal not time at the leaſt reclaime you, &amp; make you conſider of your daungerous ſtate? At the firſte perhaps phantaſie and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure mighte ouercome you, but hath not time and experience taught you to be wearie thereof? Wil you ſel heauen for the companie of a woman, or gaine eternall paines for ſo ſhort a pleaſure? becauſe you are fallen, will you neuer riſe againe? or wil you deferre til God ſodenlie take you away in the middes
<pb facs="tcp:2674:42"/>of your filthy ſinnes? or do you thinke that both ſtand well together, God his fauour, and abhominable lecherie?</p>
            <p>O M.N. you ſhould rather be ther where thoſe handes ſhould handle the bleſſed body of Chriſt, for which they were anointed and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated: where thoſe lippes ſhould ſay ordinarie <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins, Maſſe,</hi> and <hi>Euenſong,</hi> as you are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo by precepte, then to employ your whole bodie vpon the dailie doing of ſuch thinges, which good preeſts dare not thinke once vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (but againſt their wil) for feare of ſinne. Or if you can not be in place to doe as you ſhoulde, yet you may alwaies be in place to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine from that which you ſhoulde not doe.</p>
            <p>Good M. N. conſider at length the caſe deepely as it deſerueth. As it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious before God and man that you haue thus fallen, ſo it ſhal be alwaies honorable for you to riſe againe: we haue knowen maried prieſtes, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde holie men, and by their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:2674:42"/>no leſſe eſteemed then if it had neuer bene. The Church of God (as alſo God him ſelfe) is alwaies glad of a penitent ſinner, and the Angels in heauen reioiſe therat: let it ſuffice you that you haue taken your pleaſure all this time, and geue God thankes that he hath ſpared you and reſerued you al this time to repentance, wheras you might haue died in your ſinnes and ſo haue bene damned euerlaſtingly: deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe not his calling of you vnto him ſelfe and to his CATHOLIKE CHVRCH. You haue where-withall to lyue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you did forſake all. And ſo you muſte, and make away with all at once, to folow him that being God of goddes and Lorde of lords came into this world and went out of this world in all pouertie and miſerie, for your ſake, and for my ſake, and for euerye ſinners ſake, to redeeme vs vnto him ſelfe. Be not tyed any longer to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or benifice, or biſhop, or this or that. Play the man once in your time
<pb facs="tcp:2674:43"/>for God his ſake, who haue bene ſtout and ſtroung to abide the verie cutting of your body for your owne healthes ſake.</p>
            <p>O it is an honour to be compted a good mau of good men, rather then rich of the rich, and happie of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie: and a litle miſerie, or wante, or diſgrace in the world &amp; before world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, is in deede the greateſt glorie &amp; renowne before God and good men that can be wiſhed. God be thanked for it, for it is his grace and nor our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. But I thinke I may ſaye of vs all which are here no ſmal number, if vve ſhould die in baniſhment, if vve vvere driuen to begge among ſtrangers, if any miſerie ſhould befall vs, yet if vve continevve catholike and in the feare of God, al is our ioy, our crovvne, our triumphe. But to ſay trulie, vve haue all ſufficientlye, and my ſelfe vvas ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ſo good ſtate in Ingland, as here I am in all reſpectes. And yet vve in compariſon of that vvhich you might
<pb facs="tcp:2674:43"/>prouide, are of meane ſtate: you might be as greate a man beyonde the ſeas as you are there, and be ſo vvell accepted of the beſt as you vvould deſire, and it vvould be a ſingular ioye to all your frendes, and a greate honour to your ſelfe, beſids the ioy and peace of your conſcience, vvhich novv either doeth much torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you, or you are ſo much the vvorſe if you haue no feeling ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>You ſee vvhat might be ſaid if a man vvere diſpoſed to ſet your ſelfe before your ovvne eies as in a glaſſe: but I hope you are vviſe ynough to gather much of this litle: &amp; I vvould to God I had novv as good oportunitye to talke vvith you face to face as I haue had heretofore: I doubte not, by the grace of God, but I ſhould reclayme you: for I perſvvade my ſelfe that you vvould doe vvell, but the vvorld and the fleſh ouercometh you: and yet (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las) fleſh and bloud ſhall not poſſeſſe the kingdome of heauen. Thinke then
<pb facs="tcp:2674:44"/>of the loſſe of heauen, nay thincke on the paines of hell, vvhich ſhal beginne perhaps to morovv, perhaps one yere hence, and ſhal continevv for euer, for euer, for euer, (this is a long day,) and in more terrible torment then can be imagined in this life. And yet the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie goodnes and loue and benifites of God &amp; of our Sauiour Chriſt, ſhould make vs to doe vvel and to pleaſe him, more then the feare of hel paines. Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and ſeruauntes vvill not vvorke vvithout ſtripes: but children ought to doe vvell of verie loue and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Your vnlavvfull vvoman (M. N.) is but one thing (albeit a great and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible thing) but your liuing in <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> out of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating vvith heretikes, theſe are alſo of great importance. If your good L. and maſter had alſo kept his biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke and folovved the vvorld, his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample perhaps might haue diminiſhed your fault. Novv vvhat excuſe haue
<pb facs="tcp:2674:44"/>you, after the vertuous example of ſuch a prelate, of ſo many like vnto him either dead in priſon, or yet pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, or beyonde the ſeas, in loſſe of goods and countrie and frends; of ſo manie yong men and children vvhich contemne all the vvorld and vvorldie frends to folovv CHRIST and the CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOLIKE CHVRCH, and ſhal condemne ſuch as you are that ought to be lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns and lights to them? What excuſe (I ſay) haue you in this caſe, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hauing ſo manie examples of your neere frends and acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vvhom you may reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, namely that graue and learned prieſt, vvhich committed that vvoman and her children to you as to a ſpirituall patrone &amp; not a fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful father, vvho if he vvere aliue, hovv vvould you looke him in the face? An other example you haue your felovve chaplen ſometime, novv many yeres a moſte bleſſed priſoner. Whoſe happie ſtate and your ovvne miſerye if you conſider vvell, you may iuſtlye feare
<pb facs="tcp:2674:45"/>that ſaying in the Ghoſpell: <hi>Tvvo in the filde, tvvo in a bed, tvvo at the mill, the one taken &amp; the other forſaken:</hi> You may feare it I ſay, and thereby take occaſion to reclayme your ſelfe before that terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day of ſeperating the euil from the good, the reprobate from the electe &amp; choſen: When to the electe it ſhall be ſaied, come ye bleſſed, you haue done this and this for me: And to the reſte, Goe ye curſed, you haue done nether this nor that.</p>
            <p>And here I pray you thinke vvell vpon it and examine your ſelfe vvhat you haue done for Chriſt and for his Church in this time when Catholike men are proued as golde by the fire. You haue broken your vow, taken a woman, liued in pleaſure of the fleſhe, kept all liuings and perhaps increaſed them, ſaid or cauſed to be ſaid hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſeruice, interteined blaſphemous and lying preachers, flattered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the fauour of your falſe biſhopp, you haue generallie loued the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:2674:45"/>in al reſpects more then God, and that againſt your conſcience which muſte needes condemne you. And are theſe (trowye) the meanes to come to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? No, no.
<note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Per multas tribulationes opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet intrare in regnum co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lorum. By many tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations vve muſt enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> And,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Qui me negauerit coram homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, negabo &amp; ego eum coram patremeo. But he that ſhall deny me before men, I alſo vvill deny him before my father vvhich is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> For Gods loue (M.N.) thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it betimes, and diſpatche at once, and beare with my boldnes and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which is neceſſary for your ſoules health, as your ſelfe will confeſſe if it may pleaſe God to ſend you his grace and his ſpirit abundantlie to make you a new man.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall I loue you and honour you more then euer I did, and all good men with me, who do not maruel that you or anie man ſhould fall, whereas we are all ſinners and haue all ſallen one way or an other but if after admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition
<pb facs="tcp:2674:46"/>you will not riſe agayne, that wil make vs to maruel, &amp; to pitie your eaſe as altogether deſperate, which God forbid, whoe conuerte you and ſaue you and bleſſe you both ſoule &amp; bodye, euen as I wiſhe to mine owne ſelfe: For a farewel, remember the later ende of man, the accompte to be made, the conſequent there of, hel or heauen, and before all other reſpectes doe well for his ſake that made you, redeemed you, ſanctified you, and hath hitherto preſerued and enriched you, and will hereafter in heauen fully rewarde you, if you wil come euen now at the ninth and eleuenth howre. Our Lord keepe you.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Paris. <date>15. Fe. 1580</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your louing frend vndoubtedly <hi>G. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:46"/>
            <head>TO MY LOVINGE AND BESTBELOVED SISTERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EERE Siſters, my care, my loue, &amp; of al worldly things (next to my good mother) my greateſt comforte and ioye. Vnleſſe you did thinke, that I doe moſt hartely loue you, you coulde nor alwaies heretofore haue declared your exceeding loue ſo plentifully towards me, for the which almightie God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde you. This my loue becauſe it is not a naturall affection onely, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and true charitie, forceth me to wiſh vnto you, my louing Siſters, not onelie manie worldlie commodities, which (God be thanked) you lacke not: but much more, all ſpirituall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and heauenlie riches, wherof you can not haue great ſtore, becauſe you dwell not where it groweth.</p>
            <p>I know good Siſters, that you meane well, and moſte willing are you to doe that which might pleaſe God: but in
<pb facs="tcp:2674:47"/>good ſooth you are out of the way, and therefore the further you hold on, the further you are from your iornies end, the further from heauen. The wiſe man ſaith: <hi>There is a vvay vvhich ſeemeth to a man right,
<note place="margin">Prouerb. 14.</note> but the end therof leadeth to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction.</hi> Beare with me if I write bold. lie, and tell you the truth plainlie. I am your brother, I loue you (as nature bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me) not onely in worldly reſpect, but much more towardes God. Your ſoules are deare vnto me: my harte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies mourneth to thinke vpon your dangerous ſtate wherein you ſtand. O good Siſters, the paine of hell excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all tormentes, and that fier ſhall burne for euer. Happye are they that keepe them ſelues by God his greate goodneſſe within the CATHOLIQVE CHVRCH, for out of it, <hi>there is no hope of ſaluation:</hi> And moſt happy are they that hauing bene out of this Church by the wicked perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of falſe preachers, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſeth God to ſend them true teachers, will not remaine obſtinate,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:47"/>but folow good exhortations and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine, and ſo returne agayne as obedient children to Chriſt their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to the Church their mother, who are alwaies redy to receiue them: remembring that which a moſt aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and learned Father writeth.
<note place="margin">S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 88. pſal.</note> 
               <hi>He can neuer accompt God to be his father, vvho vvil not haue the Churh to be his mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you aſke me what this Church is, that is called CATHOLIKE, and how you may know it, behold the true and certen markes thereof, and your ſelfe iudge whether you be within it or no. This Church is a congregation of all true chriſtians which began in Chriſt &amp; his diſciples at Hieruſ lem, &amp; from thence grewe and multiplied through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole world, according as it is ſayd in the pſalme: <hi>Their ſounde</hi> (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Apoſtles) <hi>is gone out into the vvhole vvorlde,
<note place="margin">pſal. 18. v. 5.</note> and their vvordes into the ends of the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The firſte mark of the Church is to be viſible.</note> So that the firſt marke of the true church is, that it muſt grow and multiply, be ſeene and appeere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb facs="tcp:2674:48"/>as a light in the world: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt calleth it <hi>A Cittie builded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a hill,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> vvhich can not be hid.</hi> And the bleſſed Martyr S. Ciprian ſayth: The Churche beinge lightened with the brightnes of our Lorde, doth reache foorth her beames through-out the whole worlde. And S. Auſten beſides manye other places to this purpoſe, compareth Chriſt and his Church to that <hi>ſtone vvhich vvas cutt out of a hill vvithout mens handes,
<note place="margin">Daniel. ca. 2.</note> and after grevv to be a mightye mountayne, ſo that it filled the vvhole earthe.</hi> For vndoubtedlye this ſtone whereof the Prophet ſpeaketh is Chriſt, who was borne of a virgin without the helpe of man, and is now growne from a few Apoſtles and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to an infinite number of chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an people in all countries, confeſſing one fayth and one beleefe: and this is the Catholicke Church, whereof your Creede telleth and teacheth you to ſay. <hi>I beleeue the</hi> CATHOLIKE CHVRCH.</p>
            <p>Let vs ſee nowe whether this
<pb facs="tcp:2674:48"/>marke doth agree to your brethren in England who call them ſelues Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, or to vs whom it pleaſeth them to cal Papiſts. Firſt they cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-ſelues in their bookes the Engliſhe church, that is to ſay, of that fayth which is profeſſed in England: but we are of the CATHOLIKE CHVRCH, that is of ſuch a fayth as is profeſſed in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> in <hi>Flanders, Brabant, zelant</hi> &amp;c. In a great part of <hi>Germanie,</hi> in all <hi>Italy,</hi> and beyond, whereſoeuer there be chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and is now preached to the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that neuer heard of Chriſt before, and encreaſeth wonderfullye. And within theſe fortie yeares, in <hi>Englande, Scotland, Ireland, Denmarke,</hi> and <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> there was no other faith openly profeſſed but ours. And now alſo in all theſe countries, how many are there thinke you of ſecret catholickes that wiſh for the olde religion againe with all their hart, and folow the new onely for feare? Nay how many are there eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in <hi>England</hi> that doe yet open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2674:49"/>profeſſe the CATHOLIKE FAITH?</p>
            <p>Aſke good Siſters aſke, and you ſhall learne that all the priſons not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>London,</hi> but of <hi>England</hi> are full of them, becauſe they will not yeeld to theſe new proceedings, nor contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate their ſoules with this newe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and leaue the olde true and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke fayth: beſides a number of ſundrye degrees, which are deade in priſon: namely twentie three Biſhops all depryued of their liuing theſe twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie three yeres, &amp; now but two of them alyue: I omit <hi>Doctors, Deanes, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Krights, Squires,</hi> partlie in priſon, partly departed the Realme and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking all, rather then they will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake God; and his moſte true and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted religion. This is true (good Siſters) as knoweth God, you ſeldome heare of theſe things, and therfore you thinke either their is no other religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but that could ſeruice with-out all comfort and deuotion which you ſee in your pariſh church, or you thinke
<pb facs="tcp:2674:49"/>that muſt needes be the beſt, becauſe you are not taught anie other: whereas you ſee (if you beleeue me) that all chriſtendome almoſt is of an other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And therfore this is the CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOLIKE CHVRCH, and yours is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily called by your owne miniſters, the church of England.</p>
            <p>But this ſhall better appeere,
<note place="margin">The ſecond marke is ſucceſſiou.</note> if I geue you an oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r marke of the true &amp; Catholicke Church, which is, that it muſt continew for euer, and from the firſt beginninge, which was in Chriſt and his Apoſtles, neuer to fayle, but to appeere and be ſeene ſtill as a citrye vpon a hill, or a light in the world.
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.</note> For Chriſt ſaid: <hi>I vvill be vvith you vnto the ende of the vvorld:</hi> And againe: <hi>I vvill ſende you an other Comforter, the ſpirite of truth vvho ſhall remaine vvith you for euer.</hi> And vnto Peter: <hi>Vpon this rocke vvill I build my Church,
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> and the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it.</hi> That is to ſay, the deuill and all his miniſters, ſhall neuer ſo preuayle againſt this church, but
<pb facs="tcp:2674:50"/>that it ſhall ſtill appeere and profeſſe one, and the ſame fayth. So that there ſhall be no time, wherin this fayth and this church is not.</p>
            <p>Now marke (good Siſters) I pray you hartely, whether your Engliſhe church, and your Engliſhe religion hath bene alwayes in the worlde ſince Chriſt his time. I will ſpeake vnto you as before God, and as I ſhall anſweare before him at the later day, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I requeſte you to marke well my wordes and to conſider of them. A whole thowſande and fiue hundred yeres after Chriſt, your Engliſh religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not heard of in any parte of the world, but I tolde you before, that the true church muſt continewe for euer, &amp; appeare alwaies, vnleſſe you thinke Chriſt is falſe of his promiſe. When began your religion then? Forſooth about fiftie veres agone, by one <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Luther</hi> in Germanie a frier: who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well for other vngodly reſpects, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo becauſe he would needes marie and
<pb facs="tcp:2674:50"/>breake his vow which he had made of chaſtitie, began to preach againſt the POPE, and againſt the CATHOLIQVE CHVRCH, and becauſe he taught great libertie, as that Princes ought not to reuerence the POPE, that all Preeſtes might mary, that no man neede to faſt, and ſuch like: he found many diſciples in Germanye, and hath vnto this day carnall and fleſhly men that loue their owne pleaſure, more then the will of God, and his holy church.</p>
            <p>But will you know what manner of man this was? Forſooth being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by learned men concerning his doctrine, he was ſo preſt and ſo angred with the force of truth, that he ſayd in a great rage: <hi>This quarrell vvas neuer begon for Gods ſake, neither for his ſake ſhall it be ended.</hi> Will you know further that he wrote againſt the POPE for malice and not for conſcience? himſelfe in his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Argentmenſes</hi> fayeth: <hi>I neither can deny, neither vvill I, that if Carolſtadius or any other man could fiue yeares agone haue
<pb facs="tcp:2674:51"/>perſvvaded me that in the Sacrament is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but bread and vvine, he might haue deſerued of me great thankes: for I labored in that matter very carefully, knovving righte vvell that by that meanes, I might much haue hindred the Popes authoritie.</hi> Marke that this man would gladly haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſome-what agaynſt the BLESSED SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRAMENT, but a long time he could not, till at length the deuill had taught him to wryte agaynſt the Maſſe,
<note place="margin">De miſſa angulari.</note> as him ſelfe witneſſeth in his bookes, where he telleth what talke he and the deuill had together. Much more could I tell you of this man: but of this little you may iudge whether you may aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to build your faith vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this man, who lyued within theſe fiftye yeares, and to forſake the auncient fayth of all Chriſtendome continewed from Chriſt vntill this day: for it is moſte certen that from this man came your new religion into England, but not immediatly at the firſt when he began to preach, for Kinge <hi>Henrye</hi> the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ight,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:51"/>wrote a learned booke very earneſtly againſt him,
<note place="margin">The Quenes M. father wrote a lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned booke a gaiuſt Luther for the pope. Afterward he forſooke him not vpon religion or conſcience but vpon diſpleaſure.</note> which is common to be ſeene, but long after, partly when the King began to take diſpleaſure againſt the POPE, becauſe he might not be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and vnmaried as he liſt: Partly and eſpecially, when King <hi>Edvvard</hi> being in the beginning of his raigne but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry child, was oueruled by wicked cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers to maintayne ſuch a religion as might beſt agree to their carnall appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite. This was the beginning of your religion; the beginning I ſay, for as for King <hi>Heury,</hi> he wente nothing ſo farre as they are now come: but whereas for his pleaſure he had put awaye the Popes authority, and for his profit had plucked downe Abbaies, he let all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poyntes in man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r remayne as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and of this alſo rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nted before he died, as it is knowen, if not? wo be vnto him that euer he was borne: for there in the next world (good Siſters) Kings and Queenes come to their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, as well as you and we poore
<pb facs="tcp:2674:52"/>folkes.</p>
            <p>I could here tell you of many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and vertuous men that were then put to death, becauſe they would not yeeld to the King in his vnlawfull do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: knowing right well that it was all contrary to the lawe of God. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom were theſe two: The Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> the moſt vertuous and beſt learned of all the Clergie, as appeareth by his books. And <hi>Sir Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Moore</hi> Lorde Chauncel or of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land a lay man, who for his vertue, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and learning paſſed all tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral men that euer were in that Realme, as appeareth by his learned workes written in the Engliſhe tongue, but now not ſuffered to be redd, becauſe they teach the CATHOLIQVE FAYTH: Some man will tel you, that they were behedded for treaſon; but beleeue him not, vnleſſe it be treaſon to obay God rather then Princes, ſurely other treaſon they committed none.</p>
            <p>One Marke more I will ſhew you
<pb facs="tcp:2674:52"/>to diſcerne the true Church,
<note place="margin">The thir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e marke is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</note> &amp; that in few wordes, but ſo playne that your ſelfe will confeſſe it. To know the CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOLIKE CHVRCH, this is a certayne and an vnfallible marke, if it be in vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and concorde? if it haue an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conſent of hartes and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: that is to ſaye, if it haue but one fayth and one religion.
<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> For of the true Church it is ſayd: <hi>The vvhole multitude of beleeuers had one hart and one mynd.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> And S. Paule ſayth: <hi>One God, one fayth, one bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</hi> And againe:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> 
               <hi>God is not a God of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention, but of peace and vnitye.</hi> Looke now &amp; conſider the ſtate of your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in England onely, are they all of one religion? Haue you not among them, ſome <hi>Lytherans,</hi> ſome <hi>Caluiniſts,</hi> ſome <hi>Puritanes,</hi> all agreeing againſt the POPE, and ech diſagreeing one from the other? Do not your <hi>Luther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> preach yea before the Queene, not with-out great thankes for their labour, that the body of Chriſt is really preſent in the Sacrament? And doe not your <hi>Caelui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:53"/>preach cleane contrary, that there is onely breade and wine? And as for your <hi>Puritanes</hi> doe not they preach and wryte ſo farre contrary from the other two, that they are now forbidden to preach and caſt into priſon, and put from all liuings? Yea the communion booke it ſelfe doth it not nowe ſaye cleane contrary to that which it ſayed in the later end of King <hi>Henry</hi> his time? Then you were expreſlye commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to beleeue that vnder each kind of bread and wine are conteyned the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud of Chriſt, now it is petty treaſon to fay ſo? I ſpeake not here of <hi>Dermarke,</hi> of <hi>Geneua,</hi> of other cities in Germanve, who are all Proteſtants, and all differing among them ſelues, and from you. I haue onely declared how great diuerſitie and diſagreeing their is amonge your Proteſtantes at home within one little Ilande: which is ſo euident, and ſo farre from good chriſtianitie, that it may be vnto you a very certen and ſuer token, that the
<pb facs="tcp:2674:53"/>true fayth can not be amonge them, which hitherto can not agree in one fayth, each condemning the others o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion.</p>
            <p>Thus (derely beloued, and my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry louinge Siſters) I haue geuen you certen generall Markes to learne the true Church: To wryte all were infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, becauſe all bookes are full of our religion, I truſt hereafter to inſtructe you in euery pointe, as you would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and I pray God geue you grace, that you may deſire it: All at once woulde be to tedious: In the meane time reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber theſe two things: <hi>VVhen your religion began,</hi> and <hi>by vvhom,</hi> and how it came at length into England. This is the yeare of Chriſt a thowſand fiue hundred, eyghty and three. <hi>Luther</hi> began to preache with-in theſe fiftye yeares: If he preached the truth, and all before him were deceaued, where was the Church of Chriſt in all the worlde for a thowſande and fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares before? and how is Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:2674:54"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue of his promis, that ſayd: <hi>I vvill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne vvith you for euer, and the holy Ghoſt ſhall teach you all truth, and the gates of hell ſhall not prcu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ile againſt it:</hi> But for out Church, that is to ſay the CATHOLIKE CHVRCH, we can ſhew how it is grown and continued from the Apoſtles vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this day, and neuer fayled: We can reccon you from time to time, <hi>Councels, Biſhopps, Doctors,</hi> infinite numbers of good chriſtians of all ages that were all of our fayth and of our Church. Can your Miniſters denye but that <hi>S. Chriſoſtome</hi> alloweth <hi>praying to Saints?</hi> or that <hi>S. Ierome</hi> calleth the Biſhoppe of Rome <hi>Supreme head of the vvhole Church vnder Chriſt?</hi> or that <hi>S. Auſten prayed for his mother being dead?</hi> or that he honored <hi>the Reliques of S. Steuen?</hi> or that <hi>S. Gregory ſayd Maſſe?</hi> or that <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> ſayeth, <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vvords of conſecration it is bread and vvine, but after the vvords are ſpoken by the preiſt it is the very body and bloud of Chriſt</hi> or that all chriſtians in <hi>S. Auſtens</hi> time, <hi>did vvorſhip the bleſſed Sacrament?</hi> or that
<pb facs="tcp:2674:54"/>the ſecond Councell of <hi>Nice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeares agoe, <hi>allovve the vſe of Images for the memorie and repreſentation of Chriſt and his ſayntes?</hi> condemning <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage breakers:</hi> or that S. <hi>Barnerd</hi> was an <hi>Abbot</hi> and <hi>had monkes vnder him,</hi> as in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike countryes now a dayes? can they deny but that all this is true? and dare they deny theſe vertuous Fathers, and Doctors of the Church to be now Saints in heauen?</p>
            <p>O my good Siſters, that you could vnderſtand their books and their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, that you might your ſelues ſee what they ſay, and what wonderfull men they were, endued with the ſpirit of God exceedingly aboue other euen good men, much more then your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious leaders, I doubt not but you would ſuſpect your new doctors, and folow theſe: you ſhould perceaue they had the ſcriptures at their fingers eds, they knew right well the meaning and ſenſe thereof, night and day by faſting and prayer, and chaſt lyfe, beſeeching
<pb facs="tcp:2674:55"/>God that they might vnderſtand and truly expound his word. O what a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there betweene them and theſe new Preachers? Siſters, I appeale to your conſciences, whither wil you, or ought you to truſte in the expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Scripture, your yong vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; fleſhly Miniſters; or theſe aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, moſt ſkilfull, and moſt vertuous Fathers?</p>
            <p>When Chriſt ſayed:
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Take, eate, this is my body:</hi> Al theſe Fathers ſay and agree that it was his bodye in verye deede: Your miniſters tell you it was but bread and wine.
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> When Chriſt ſayed to <hi>Peter, thou art Peter, that is a rocke, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this rocke vvill I build my Church.</hi> Theſe Fathers ſay that <hi>Peter</hi> was made <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> and after him all his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors in the See of Rome where <hi>Peter</hi> was the firſt Biſhopp: Your Miniſters tell you that <hi>Peter</hi> had no more prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaunce then the other Apoſtles, &amp; therfore the Biſhop of Rome hath no more authoritie then an other biſhop
<pb facs="tcp:2674:55"/>hath. When Chriſt ſayed to his Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles: <hi>Receaue ye the holy ghoſt,
<note place="margin">Io. 20.</note> vvhat ſoeuer ye doo looſe in earth, ſhalbe looſed in heauen, and vvhat ſoeuer ye doe binde in earth it ſhal be bounde in heauen:</hi> Theſe Fathers ſaye that Chriſt gaue to his Church autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to remit ſinne by the miniſtrie of the preiſt to all ſuch as doe truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and therefore will haue the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple goe to Confeſſion: Your miniſters haue taken that comfortable Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of penance away altogether. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Raphael</hi> the Angel ſayth in the twelfth chapter of Tobias: <hi>That he did offer vp Tobias prayer to almightie God.</hi> And when in the ſecond booke of <hi>Macchabees</hi> the fifteenth chapter, <hi>Onias</hi> the prieſt ſaith of <hi>Ieremie</hi> being dead <hi>This is he that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth much for his people, and for the holie citie:</hi> theſe fathers ſay, that the <hi>Angells</hi> and <hi>Sainctes</hi> doo praye for vs, and that we may pray to them: your miniſters doe not ſtricke to ſay, that theſe books of <hi>Tobie,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Macchabces</hi> are ſcant good ſcripture.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:56"/>
            <p>Many other things lyke vnto theſe I could reccon, but I ſhould be to lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, fearing leaſt I ſhould werie you, theſe fewe are ſufficient to geue you to taſte of ſuch marks as may ſhew you the CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOLIKE CHVRCH. Theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great reaſons doe keepe all good chriſtians within the Church. Theſe thinges make ſo many catholiks, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue ſuffred death: partly to haue died in priſon: partly to continew in priſon ſo many yeares: partly to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their pleaſant countrie, their dere frends, and to liue to their conſcience among ſtrangers, being thought of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worldly men to be very fooles for ſo doing: but they know right wel that the wiſdome of this worlde is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes before God.
<note place="margin">Mat. 10</note> And Chriſt ſayth, <hi>He that loueth father and mother, ſiſter and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, better then me, is not vvorthie of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Siſters geue me leaue to tell you ſome-what of my ſelfe, not for anye bragge, but the more to moue you and to geue God all the praiſe for his great
<pb facs="tcp:2674:56"/>goodnes towardes me. It pleaſed my parentes to bring me vp in learning as you know, as I was not the beſt, ſo I was at al times not compted the worſt among my felowes and companions: ſome ſmall eſtimation I had in <hi>Oxforde</hi> aboue my deſert, more afterwards whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſed the <hi>Duke</hi> to make me though vnworthy, Tutor to the <hi>Erle</hi> his ſonne: as long as his grace did proſper, I liued in his howſe to my conſcience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trouble: when he was in the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp; other men ruled his howſe, I was willed to receaue the Communion, or to depart: if I would haue yeelded, I had verye large offers which I neede not tell. It pleaſed God to ſtaye me ſo with his grace, that I choſe rather to forſake all then to doe agaynſt my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, againſt my knowledge, agaynſt my conſcience, agaynſt the law of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God: For a time I lay ſecretly in England, afterwards I came beyond the ſeas into theſe catholicke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, out of ſchiſme and hereſie: for the
<pb facs="tcp:2674:57"/>which I do tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke almighty God much more, then for all the eſtimation that I had or mighte haue had in Englande. Whatſoeuer my eſtate is here, I doe more eſteeme it, then all the riches of England as it now ſtandeth.</p>
            <p>And were I ſo mad thinke you to forſake all preferment, all liuinges, all eſtimation, to liue from my good Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from you my louinge Siſters and your huſbandes, from other my deere frendes and companions, out of mine owne moſt pleaſant countrie, would I doe this thinke you, but that my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; my conſcience telleth me, that to ſolow your religion is preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of body and ſoule: and to be in the CATHOLIKE CHVRCH is the onely way to ſaluation? Fye vpon all worldy ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches when the ſoule is in danger: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo precious as the ſoule: firſt ſeeke for the kingdome of heauen, &amp; for other things as it pleaſeth God. O that I might vnderſtand once, that you were of my mind, and of the catholike
<pb facs="tcp:2674:57"/>religion: O my harte would leape for ioy, to conſider that althoughe we can not lyue together vpon earth, yet we may hereafter meete in heauen: which is vnpoſſible as long as we diſagree in fayth. S. Paule ſayeth: <hi>There is one God, one fayth, one baptiſme. S. Auſten</hi> ſayeth, ſpeaking of one <hi>Emeritus, He can not be ſaued but in the Catholicke Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe you thinke it ſufficient to beleeue in the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt?
<note place="margin">Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 88 pſalme.</note> Harken what S. <hi>Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſayth: <hi>VVhat doth it profit thee, if thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the Lord? If thou bonour God? If thou preach and praiſe him? If thou acknovvledge his Sonne? If thou confeſſe that he ſitteth at the right hand of his father? VVhat dooth this profit thee, if thou blaſpheme his Churche? S. Athanaſius</hi> in his creede ſaith: <hi>VVhoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer vvil be ſaued it is neceſſarie that he holde the Catholicke faith, vvhich faith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man beleeue in all points, and euery ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, vvithout doubt</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>he ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh euerlaſtingly.</hi> One poynte is (good Siſters) that Chriſt gaue vs at his laſte
<pb facs="tcp:2674:58"/>ſupper, his owne bleſſed bodye and bloude to feede vpon in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his bitter death: he that ſaith it is not ſo, doth he beleeue in Chriſt? Doth he not in effecte ſay that Chriſt was not able to doe it, and by that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he was not omnipotent? For when the three Euangeliſts reporte it ſo playnly,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26. Mat. 14. Luc. 22. 1. Cor. 11.</note> &amp; S. Paule after them: <hi>Take, eate,</hi> THIS IS MY BODY, <hi>that ſhall be dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered for you:</hi> THIS IS MY BLOVD <hi>that ſhall be ſhed for you:</hi> What maketh a man to doubt but that it is ſo in deede? O you will ſay, I ſee nothing but bread and wine. If you ſhould ſee his body, no god a mercy if you did beleeue it: But Chriſt ſayed to Thomas: <hi>Thou Thomas doeſt beleeue becauſe thou haſt ſeene,
<note place="margin">10.20.</note> but hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py are they that beleeue vvhen they ſee not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I pray you when the three wiſe men came from the Eaſt to worſhip Chriſt, what did they ſee in him? Forſooth a yong infant, not able to helpe himſelfe ſuckinge his mother a poore carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wyfe, and that in an oxe ſtawle:
<pb facs="tcp:2674:58"/>yet they fell downe and worſhipped him as a God: Is it not as eaſie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the body of Chriſt is vnder the forme of bread, as that almightie God himſelfe was then vnder the ſhape of a ſeely weake infante? O good Siſters, vnleſſe you beleeue, you ſhall neuer vnderſtande: beleeue once Ghriſt his wordes, and that he is Almightie, and that he is able to doe what ſoeuer he ſayeth, and you will thinke that all is eaſye: returne to the CATHOLIKE CHVRCH, and be content to learne that which you know not, of them that wil not for all the world deceaue you, and you ſhal fynde exceeding comfort.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt ſhall ſay at the later day, as it were in this maner. Was it not of my great kyndnes that I lefte vnto you mine owne body and bloud? And was it not of my exceedinge goodnes and wiſdome to leaue it, not in the forme of fleſh and bloud, leaſt your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould abhorre it, but of bread &amp; wyne which can be lothſome to no
<pb facs="tcp:2674:59"/>man? and you make me this gaye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, ſaying that it was nothing but bread &amp; wyne, becauſe you could taſt nothing els in your mouth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your new preachers tould you ſo, whom I ſente not? Were not you chriſtened in an other fayth? Did not my church <hi>vvhich is my ſpouſe</hi> and <hi>the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 21</note>
               <note place="margin">1. Timo. 3.</note> alwayes teach otherwayes? What haue you to ſaye for your ſelfe, but that you haue moſt vukindly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that BLESSED SACRAMENT and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly miſterie, and make me a lyer, and deny my omnipotencie, and therefore deſerue eternall damnation with all ſuch as haue deceaued you?</p>
            <p>When Chriſt ſhall ſay this, will it not be a heauye caſe? When <hi>Cyprian, Ambroſe, Chriſoſtome, Auſten, Ierom, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Bernard,</hi> all the olde Fathers now Saints in heauen, ſhall come and beare witneſſe againſt you, and ſay that they taught otherwiſe? When your Biſhops that are now partly deade, and partly in priſon for the defendinge of this
<pb facs="tcp:2674:59"/>cauſe, ſhal condemne you becauſe you did not folowe their good example? When your owne doctors &amp; teachers ſhall not be able to anſwere for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, will it not be a pitifull caſe? But I hope better of you (good Siſters) I can not miſtruſte your good natures, but that you will be glad to learne the truth: which almighay God graunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you for his deere Sonnes ſake who died for vs: and that I may heare ſome comfortable newes from you.</p>
            <p>Doe but ſignifie vnto me that you are content, if any thing be amiſſe, to be better inſtructed. Proue me what I can ſay for any thinge that trowbleth your conſciences: It ſhall be farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter newes vnto me, to receaue two lines from you to ſuch a purpoſe, then to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that your huſbands were made Lords and you Ladies. He is rich that is in the Catholike Church, and he is honorable that is in the fauour of God. Siſters if I might doe you good to God-warde, I would not ſticke to
<pb facs="tcp:2674:60"/>aduenture this body of myne to ſaue your ſoules, to come and talke with you: my bodye is not more precious vnto me then your ſoules: How you are diſpoſed, &amp; what you would haue me to doe for your ſakes let me vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the next. Deale wiſely I pray you &amp; warily both for your owne ſake and for our good frend this berer: It is not reaſon that for his good will he ſhould incurre any danger: God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid: my truſte is in your wiſdome that you will keepe this very cloſe til here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after by reaſon of the great perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The matter is waighty and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth both you and this berer verye much: be wiſe and truſty, and deceaue not your brother that loueth you as himſelfe, and therefore wiſheth by all meanes to do you good. S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth: <hi>He that hath not regard of his ovvne kindred,
<note place="margin">1. Timoth. 5.</note> hath denied the fayth, and is vvorſe then an Infidell:</hi> S. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame place wryteth thus: <hi>If a man inſtruct ſtrangers in the fayth, and ſuffer his ovvne kinne to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevve
<pb facs="tcp:2674:60"/>in their error vvith vvhom he vvere lykelly to preuaile moſt, becauſe they make moſt accompt of him, vvere he not a moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and barberous man?</hi> For this cauſe I wryte vnto you, and wiſh you al grace, al goodnes, al heauenly comfort: laſte of all, and leaſt of all, to proſper in this world, and yet I wiſh you that with all my hart at the pleaſure of God.</p>
            <p>Other good thing I haue none to ſende you but this, I will remayne in your debte for your gentle tokens. Commend me to your ſelues, your lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing huſbands, and your litle ones: and when you haue learned to beleeue ryght your ſelues, bringe them vp ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, &amp; teach them to feare God. Make much of this berer I praye you: and ſaue him harmeleſſe by your wyſe and diſcreate dealings. Almighty God preſerue you, and by his holy ſpirite leade you into all truth.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:61"/>
            <head>THE COPY OF A LETTER WRITTEN TO M. DOCTOVR Whyte Warden of the new Colledge in Oxforde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>YGHTE Worſhipfull, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though your worldly dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and the iuſte opinion of your greate wyſdome compared with my contraries mighte feare me from writing vnto you in this bould maner, yet many thinges moued me, eſpecially my charitie towardes you to whom I am beholding for cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which you may remember, and my dewtie towards God, whoſe good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I hope it was, that I ſhould tell you rather frendly then finely, playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> curiouſly, that which your ſelfe doe knowe much better, but haue not cauſe ſo well to remember:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe that vexation doth geue vnderſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> and <hi>man vvhen he vvas in honor did not vnderſtand.</hi> Which differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in eſtate, maketh that
<pb facs="tcp:2674:61"/>the yonger man for yeres &amp; more ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for wit and knowledge, may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſometime truly ſay with the prophete:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 118.</note> 
               <hi>Aboue auncients haue I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. Quare doctoralis ille faceſſat ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor cuiuſcunque dignitatis recedat ambitio: cum fratre &amp; conſeruo meo, filig matris eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiae, diſcipulo Ieſu Chriſti loquor. Therefore ſetting a ſide that doctor all honour and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of vvhat dignitie ſoeuer, I may be bould to ſpeake playnely vvith my brother and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv-ſeruant in Chriſt, vvith a childe of our Mother the Church and a ſcholler of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preſuppoſing then that you are in conſcience a catholike, and ſeing that in outward ſhew you profeſſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, I am bould to reaſon familiarly with you, and to demaunde: whether you thinke it lawfull to beleeue one thing inwardly, &amp; to proteſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary openly? and how you can auoyd theſe euident ſcriptures: <hi>VVith the harte vve beleeue to Iuſtice:</hi> But when there is neceſſary occaſion:
<note place="margin">Ro. 10.10</note> 
               <hi>VVith the mouth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb facs="tcp:2674:62"/>is made to ſaluation. He that ſhal deny me before men,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.33.</note> I alſo vvill deny him before my Father vvhich is in heauen.</hi> But if you thinke it vnlawfull ſo to doe, (becauſe you wote well it is condemned of old in the hereticks called <hi>Helceſaitiſtes</hi> and <hi>Priſcilianiſtes</hi>) and yet doe agaynſt your owne perſwaſion,
<note place="margin">Buſcb. li. 6. ca. 31. Aug. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Mendac. Cap. 2. Ro. 14.22.</note> how anſwere you theſe places: <hi>Bleſſed is he that iudgeth not himſelfe in that vvhich he approueth.</hi> And: <hi>vvhatſoeuer is not of fayth is ſinne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 6.</note> That is (as S. Auguſtine and others expounde it) <hi>reluctante conſcientia: Our conſcience ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing againſt it.</hi> If neither the one nor the other, but you are perſwaded that a man may lawfully profeſſe both religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as time and Prince altereth: Beſids that it was the hereſie of <hi>Baſilides.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 4. ca. 2.</note> Tò á<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaphore in, as <hi>Nicephorus</hi> wryteth: What interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue you for theſe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: <hi>Vſquequo claudicatis in vtramque partem &amp;c.
<note place="margin">3. Re. 18.21.</note> Hovve longe haulte you on both ſides? I four Lorde be God? ſolovv him: But if Baal? folovv him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 3.</note> And agayne: <hi>Coringre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens duas vias &amp;c. A harte that goeth tvvo
<pb facs="tcp:2674:62"/>vvayes ſhall not haue ſucceſſe, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe of harte ſhall be ſcandalized in them.</hi> And:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>you can not drincke the chalice of our Lorde, and the chalice of deuils:
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.24. Mat. 12.30.</note> you can not ſerue tvvo Maiſters. He that gathereth not vvith me ſcattereth.</hi> And agayne:
<note place="margin">Iac. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Doth the fountayne geue foorth at one hole ſvveete and ſovver vvater?</hi> And yet agayne:
<note place="margin">Apoc. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art lukevvarme, and neither could nor vvhot, I vvill begin to vomit thee out of my mouth.</hi> I neede not vrge the terrible threatenings, your wiſdome may car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly conſider of it.</p>
            <p>But it is poſſible that you miſlyke of certen things in the Catholicke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which you would wiſh to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, and conceaue a mixte religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, compounded of that which is beſt in both. But M. Doctor, you are in myne opinion wyſer then they whoe notwithſtanding for this ſingularitie are eſteemed to be wyſe men, and of graue iudgement, but of the vnwyſer ſort. You know concerning things to be miſlyked, ether they pertayne to
<pb facs="tcp:2674:63"/>fayth or to manners: If theſe later of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, you wot what <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> hath long agone anſwered the Donatiſtes: <hi>Tollerare eccleſiam, non probare, paleas in tanta copia eſſe vt frumentum tegant, donec veniat is qui ventilabrum habet in manu ſua vt purget aream ſuam. That the Church doth tollerate and not approue them, and that their is ſo great quantitie of chaffe that it couereth the corne, till he come that hath the fanne in his hand to purge his floore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any poynte of doctrine agreed vpon by the whole Church (which is alwayes directed by the holy Ghoſte) miſlyketh you? you may vpon deeper conſideration, iuſtlye feare leſte your ſelfe, or any other man in this caſe be not a true Catholicke, nor of that Church, out of which is no ſaluation: For that which is the grounde of your fayth in one poynt muſt conſequently be the grounde of it in all the reſt. So that if you beleeue (as you doe) the preſence of Chriſt in the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, becauſe the vniuerſal Church
<pb facs="tcp:2674:63"/>out of the ſcriptures hath ſo conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: then if the ſame Church doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine any other Article, for example, <hi>Of Purgatorie, of praying to Saincts, of Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, of Pardons, of Images,</hi> you muſt in like maner beleeue the ſame. If not? What authoritie doe you folow? What doe you make your grownd? but your ſinguler fancie, as in theſe, ſo in all the reſt which you ſeeme to beleeue,</p>
            <p>Farre from the obedience which the Apoſtle teacheth: Captiuatinge their vnderſtanding to the obedience of fayth:
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.3.</note> And very wide from <hi>S. Auſtens</hi> moſte learned and humble opinion.
<note place="margin">Contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cy. funda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Non crederem Euangelio niſi authoritas Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae me moueret: I vvoulde not beleeue the Ghoſpell, except the authoritie of the Church did moue me.</hi> He that ſayed ſo, would he not alſo vpon occaſion offered bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and confidently haue ſayd: I beleeue their is Purgatorye, that their are Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons in the Church, that we may pray to Sainctes, becauſe the Church doth teach me to beleeue ſo. And if you aſke
<pb facs="tcp:2674:64"/>him what church, he wold ſend you to his long treatiſes againſt the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> &amp; ſhew you as in a glaſſe a very liuely diſcription of this preſent CATHOLIKE ROMANE GHVRCH. No dout the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Church is ether ſo neceſſary or ſo ſufficient a foundation to builde vpon, that without the warrantiſe of it a man beleeueth nothing, becauſe he beleeueth his owne braynes: and with it, a man may and ought euen agaynſt humane reaſon beleeue any thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the Oracle of the holye Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>And in good ſooth, it is a ſmall reaſon to credite one article and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credite an other, both defined by the Church. As to ſaye: this is golde and this is copper, both being tryed golde by the tou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch ſtone. As much to ſay in playne wordes, this I will, and this I will not.
<note place="margin">Proſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. pru. P. 2.0.27</note> 
               <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yolo, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iubeo, ſtet proratione voluntas.</hi> Vnnaturall children, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in deede no true children, that deuideth their mother the Church, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:2674:64"/>this, miſliking that: which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>deuidere ſententiam:</hi> Euen as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mom</hi> iudged moſte truly her to be the falſe mother, that requyred moſte im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently: <hi>Be it neither to me, nor to thee: but let it be deuyded.
<note place="margin">3. Reg. 3.26. In. Pſ, 88. conc. 2.</note> Quid prodeſt ſi Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num confiteris? Deum honoras? if ſum predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas? Filium eius agnoſcis, ſedentem ad dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram patris confiteris? &amp; blaſphemas eccleſiam eius? VVhat doth it profit thee</hi> (ſayeth S. Auſten) <hi>if thou confeſſe our Lord, if thou ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, if thou prayſe him, if thoudoſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knovvledge his ſonne, and confeſſe him to ſit at the right hand of the Father, and yet doeſt blaſpheme his Church?</hi> And after he had recyted all the hereſies before, and in his tyme, he ſayeth: <hi>Omnis christianus catholicus ist a non debet credere:
<note place="margin">Ad Quodul. in ſine.</note> ſed non om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis qui ista non credit, conſequenter debet ſe christianum catholicum iam putare vel dicere. Poſſune enim &amp; haereſes aliae quae in hoc opere nostro commemoratae non ſunt, vel eſſe vel fieri, quarum aliquam quiſquis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuerit, Christianus Catholicus non erit. Euery chriſtian catholike ought not to beleeue
<pb facs="tcp:2674:65"/>theſe thinges, but it follovveth not that euery one that belecueth not theſe thinges ought to thinke and accompt him ſelfe to be a chriſtian catholike, for their may be many other here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies vvhich are not reconned vp in this booke, any one of the vvhich, vvhoſoeuer holdeth, is not a chriſtian catholike.</hi> And therfore <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi is in Symbolo</hi> ſayeth: <hi>VVhich</hi> (Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke fayth) <hi>except euery one doe keepe vvholy and inuiolable, vvithout doubte he ſhall periſh euerl eſtingly.</hi> Thus much I haue ſayed by the way, rather to you, then of you: becauſe I haue knowne certen learned and wyſe men of that miſlyking and diſtinguiſhing humor.</p>
            <p>But to you I will talke as to one that is in conſcience a full Catholicke, and for outwarde behauiour may be eſteemed contrary. <hi>S. Auſten</hi> exhorteth vs:
<note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Amemus Dominum Deum noſtrum, Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Ecclſiam eius, illum ſiout Patrem, iſtam ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut Matrem Matrimonium hoc magna cum charitate compaginatur: Nemo offendit vnum &amp; promere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur alterum. Nemo dicat ad Idola quidem vado: ſed tamen Dei eccleſiam non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquo,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:65"/>Catholicus ſum: tenens Matrem, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis Patrem &amp;c. Let vs loue our lord God, let vs loue his Church: Him as our Father, her as our Mother. This matrimonye is knitte together vvith greate charitie. No man offendeth the one, and deſerueth thankes of the other. Let no man ſay, I goe to the Idols, and yet for all that I doe not forſake Gods Church: I am a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, houlding thy Mother (in harte) and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendinge thy Father (in facte openly) &amp;c.</hi> I neede not tell you, that to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with Idolaters and with hereticks is all one,
<note place="margin">Paſſim in propheta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quia omnis hereſis Idolum eſt ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatorum eius. Becauſe all hereſie</hi> (as S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome ſayeth) is <hi>the Idoll of her follovvers.</hi> And therefore <hi>S. Auſten</hi> declaring the danger of the one to be more then the other ſayth:
<note place="margin">Vpon the. 54. Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>Ab illis qui longe ſunt facilis cautio eſt: non me tamcito fallit qui dicit: ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Idolum adorare: multum a me longe eſt. Chriſtianus es? Chriſtianus inquit: expropin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo aduerſatur, prope eſt, redime in pace ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam meam ab iis qui appropinquant mihi. VVe may eaſily bevvare of thoſe that be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farre of, for he doth not ſo ſoone deceaue me,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:66"/>vvhich ſayth: Come adore the Idoll, he is very farre from me. Art thou a chriſtian? I am a chriſtian ſayeth he: he is neere to me: he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me euen at hand: redeeme thy ſoule in peace from thoſe vvhich are neere vnto thee.</hi> S. Ambroſe: <hi>Fraterno nomine non fraterné eccleſiam perſequntur:
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Incar. Ca. 2.</note> ſiquidem ſub optione. nominis Christiani &amp; quadam nuncupatiua fidei germanitate paricidalibus gladiis nos cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt vulnerare. They perſecute the Church vnder the name of a brother, but not brotherly: truly they deſire to vvounde vs vvith their murthering ſvvord vnder the choſen name of a Christian, and a certen fayned brotherhood of fayth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the pretenſed name of a Chriſtian doth ſo eaſely procure cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite to falſe doctrine? What doth the name of a Catholicke to perſwade er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious opinions? which I beſeeche you conſider deepely. For a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke you are eſteemed, and learned and wyſe: Many good meaning men that gladly would doe well depende vpon you, harken what you ſay, looke
<pb facs="tcp:2674:66"/>what you doe, and becauſe they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to folow you, by your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ill and ſaying worſe, you doe piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully infecte many hartes, either with error or diſſimulation, and wounde their ſoules to euerlaſting death: and that becauſe they compte you a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke, and therefore are perſwaded, that you will not teach them amiſſe. Lyke as the Iewes conceyued of one <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mius</hi> the hygh Prieſt, ſaying:
<note place="margin">1. Mac. 2.</note> The man being a Prieſt of <hi>Arons</hi> ſtocke and comming vnto vs after this ſorte, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtebly will not deceaue vs. But you can well remember howe by that name and tytle he abuſed them.</p>
            <p>Surely, if Hereſie ſhould chooſe perſons for her commendation, there could be no greater pollicy, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hire ſuch as haue bene wyſe Catholicks &amp; are ſo eſteemed yet. But in deede to be a ſlaue to heretical aduauncements doth not become a wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; ſo great conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of Chriſt &amp; his Church ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſtande with the name of a Catholicke:
<pb facs="tcp:2674:67"/>Beſids that, the danger thereof is terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and with litle conſideration may iuſtly make a ſtony harte to quake and tremble. For what will you alleage at the later day? or vnder what name will you pleade for your ſaluation? <hi>VVhen he ſhall render euery man accordinge to his vvorkes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.27</note>
               <note place="margin">Amb. li. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſp. ſan. c. 18.</note> That you are a Chriſtian? But Chriſt will anſwere: <hi>Non agnoſco nomen meum, vbi non agnoſco doctrinam meam. I doe not acknovvleage my name, vvhere I doe not acknovvleage my doctrine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 49</note> That you are a Catholicke? <hi>But if thou ſavveſt a theeſe,
<note place="margin">Ro. 2.24</note> thou ranneſt after him.</hi> And my name through you is blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt hereticks.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 16.</note> And: <hi>Their belly is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vvith my ſecrets.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.</note> Of cloſe diſſembling catholicks, their congregation was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed and multiplyed. When our ſweete Sauiour (who made that nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confeſſion for euery one of vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Pontius Pilate) ſhall thus ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you that now dare not confeſſe him, will you not then wiſhe that you had prayed with the Prophete:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 118.</note> 
               <hi>Take not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay
<pb facs="tcp:2674:67"/>out of my mouth the vvord of truth vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 38.</note> And that you had donne with the Prophete: <hi>I haue not hid thy truth from the great Councell.</hi> And:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 39.</note> 
               <hi>Lo I vvill not ſtay my lippes, Lord thou haſte knovvne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Looke well vpon your perſon, your calling, your place, what a foule example it is to others, and when ſuch a man doth (I will not ſay) further, but tollerate onely and diſſemble falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Wo be to the worlde for ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals. <hi>S. Auſten</hi> hath a place much wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your conſideration.
<note place="margin">Ca. 7. de. paſtor.</note> 
               <hi>Si indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r habuero errorem tuum, attendit qui fortis eſt, put at nihil eſſe ire in haereſim. Quando ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod commodum de ſeculo illuxerit, vnde mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur ſtatim mihi dicit, fortis ille periturus: &amp; hâc &amp; hâc Deus est: quid interest? homines inter ſe litigantes hoc ſecerunt, vbicunque co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendus est Deus: ſi forte illi dixerit aliquis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natista, non tibi do filiam meam, niſi fueris de parte mea: illi opus est vt attendat &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat: ſi nihil mali eſſet de parte eorum, non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra illos dicere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta Paſtores nos<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tri, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum errore ſatagerent. Si ergo ceſſemus &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceamus
<pb facs="tcp:2674:68"/>contrar: o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loquuturus eſt. Vtique ſi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſſet in parte Donati, loquerentur contra, redarguerent eos, ſatagerent lucrarieos, ſi er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, reuocarent illos: ſi pereunt, quaererent. If I</hi> (being a paſtor or guide of others) <hi>ſhould make it</hi> (in the weaker ſorte) <hi>a matter indefferent, to be of your error, then the ſtrong in fayth vvould note it, and thincke it vvere no matter of importaunce to fall into hereſie. Therefore vvhen any commoditie that the vvorld mighte proffer by changing of his religion, the ſtronge prone to periſhe vvould ſtrayght ſay to me: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſh, God is on this ſide, and that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le, there is no difference, men onely falling at varience aboute the matter, haue made all this adoe. God may be ſerued on each hande. If ſome Donatist</hi> (ſo was the ſecte of that tyme called, as now Proteſtant or Caluiniſt) <hi>ſhould happely ſay vnto him, I vvill not besto vve my doughter vpon thee, excepte thou vvilte be of our ſecte, ſuch a one bad neede to take good beede and ſaye, if it vvere no hurte, but an indifferent matter to be of the Donatistes partye, then our Pastours vvould not ſpeake ſo many thinges agaynste
<pb facs="tcp:2674:68"/>them, they vvoulde not buſye them ſelues ſo muche aboute that errour. Therefore if vve ceaſe and hould our peace, he vvill ſaye all contrarye: Surely if it vvere ſo ill a thinge to be of the ſecte or parte of Donat, our Pastors vvoullde ſpeake agaynste it: vvould reproue them: vvould ſeeke to vvynne them: If they erred, they vvould reuoke them, if they be loſt, they vvould ſeeke them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be ſuch a blocke for other men to ſtumble at, when the learned Doctour and Paſtour doeth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute hereſie? What is it when he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and prayſeth it? Alas you can not denye, but that you doe ſo.
<note place="margin">1. cor. 8.</note> 
               <hi>And ſo through thy knovvledge, the vveeke bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall periſhe for vvhom Christ hath dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Saynte Cyprian</hi> bringeth in children,
<note place="margin">Ep. de. lapſ.</note> whoſe Parentes example made them den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Chriſte,
<note place="margin">Aug. ep. 23.</note> pleadinge for them ſelues at the daye of Iudgemente, in this manner. <hi>Nos nihil fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imus, nec dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licto cibo &amp; poculo Domini ad prophana con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agia ſponte properauimus: Perdidit nos aliena perfidia, parentes ſenſimus parrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das:
<pb facs="tcp:2674:69"/>illi nobis eccleſiam Matrem, illi Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem Deum negauerunt, vt dum parui &amp; improuidi, &amp; tanti facinoris ignari per a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios ad conſortium criminis iungimur; aliena fraude caperemur. VVe our ſelues did nothing: vve forſooke not of our ovvne accorde the meate and cupp of our Lorde, and hastened to prophane contagions: other mens faythleſnes destroyed vs. VVe felte our parentes murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of vs their ovvne children, they for vs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Church our mother, they forſooke God our Father that being in our young and vnſkilfull yeares, and vvholy ignorant of the vvickednes, vve mighte be intangled by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the felovvſhip of the ſinne, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapped by other mens fraude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the carnall children may iuſtly thus accuſe their naturall parentes in the caſe of Idolatrie? May not ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all children much more impute their damnation to their ſpirituall fathers in the cauſe of hereſie? I will not diſpute how the crymes differ to commit Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye and to preach hereſie, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a mans conſcience, but becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:2674:69"/>diſſimulation is the leaſt of them, and <hi>ſcandalizare fratres</hi> is an horrible ſinne: Therefore the authorities which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſometymes agaynſt the one, may now be aptly vſed agaynſt the other. S. Auſten: <hi>Apparet illud eſſe prohibitum, ne in honorem alienorum Deorum aliqua re vtamur, aut vti exiſtimemur,
<note place="margin">Ep. 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſic eam accipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, vt quamuis animo contaminamus eos ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men qui noſtrum animum ignorant, ad haec honoranda, aedificemus. It is euident that vve be forbidden to vſe any thing vvhatſoeuer for the honour of ſtraunge gods, or in ſuch ſorte as vve may be thought to vſe it to that end ſo taking it, that though vve in our harte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne it, vve yet prouoke them that ſee not our mindes to honor the ſame.</hi> And agayne ſpeaking of Seneca: <hi>Eo damnabilius cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat Idola, quó illa quae mendaciter agebat,
<note place="margin">De ciui. Dei li. 6. ca. 10.</note> ſic ageret, vt eum populus veraciter agere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimaret. He did ſo much more damnablye vvorſhip Idols, for that he ſo did thoſe thinges vvhich he did in fayned ſhevv onely that the people might thinke he did them truly and vnfaynedly.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:70"/>
            <p>For howe ſhall the people iudge, but accordinge as they ſee and heare? If a good meaninge or interpretation would ſerue: Peter, might haue ſayed, (as ſome olde wryters excuſed him) that <hi>dicendo,
<note place="margin">Theeph. in. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 22. Lu.</note> Neſcio bominem, illud voluiſſet, Neſcio purum hominem, ſed Dcum bominem factum: ſayinge: I knovve not the man, be meant I knovve him not for a pure man, but for God,
<note place="margin">Ep. Cleri. Roms. 31. Apnd. Cyp.</note> made man.</hi> But: <hi>Cum totum fidei Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum in confeſſione Chriſti nominis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligatur, eſſe digeſtum, qui fallaces in excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatione peaeſtigias, quaerit, negabit. Et qui vult videri propoſitis aduerſus Euangelium vel edictis vel legibus ſatisfeciſſe, hoc if ſo iam paruit quod videri paruiſſe ſe voluit. Seeing the vvhole Sacrament of fayth is knovvne to conſiſt in the confeſſion of Chriſt his name, be ſhall be deemed to deny him that ſeeketh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfull and vayne ſhifts for his excuſe. And he that vvould be compted to haue ſatified or fulfilled Lavves or ſtatutes promulgated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Ghoſpell, in that he muſt be adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to haue obeyed them, that he vvould haue him ſelfe ſeeme to haue done it.</hi> And there
<pb facs="tcp:2674:70"/>fore conſtante <hi>Eleazarus</hi> woulde not eate, no not lawfull meates,
<note place="margin">2. Mac. 6.</note> leſte it ſhould be thought he did eate meates vnlawfull. I appeale to your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence onely (for what neede I vrge e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidente places) whether theſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rityes doe not concerne you? <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> ſayeth:
<note place="margin">Li. 2. of. c. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Licet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bi ſilere in negotio dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat pecuniario, quanquam ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſtantiae adeſſe aequitati: in cauſa autem Dei, vbi communionis periculum eſt, etiam diſſimulare peccatum eſt non leue. It is lavvfull for thee in a monye matter onely to hould thy peace, though it vve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the part of a conſtant man e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen therein alſo to ſtand in a matter of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: but in the cauſe of God, vvhere commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or felovvſhip in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayth is in perill, euen to diſſemble is no ſmall ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O but it is good wiſdome to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne credit in euery worlde, and to looſe neither welth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſtimation. I wounder that any wyſe man ſhoulde thinke ſo. Much lyke as <hi>Cato Vticenſis</hi> thought it great manhood to kill him ſelfe: and the ſecular Poet calleth it
<pb facs="tcp:2674:71"/>
               <hi>Catonis nobile laetum: Cato his noble death:</hi> Whereas S. <hi>Auſten</hi> proueth it to haue bene daſtardly cowardnes, and woma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe pucillanimitye: Ryghte ſo that worldly wiſdome, <hi>is fooliſhnes vvith God:</hi> vnleſſe a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man may ſay with the vnchriſtened and prophane Oratour: <hi>Seruire temporibus ſapientis ſemper eſt habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum:
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.19.</note> It vvas alvvayes compted vviſdome to apply him ſelfe to the tyme.</hi> And <hi>Non idem ſemper dicere ſed idem ſemper ſpec<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tare debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. VVe ought not to ſpeake the ſame thing advvayes, but to approue the ſame thing ſtill.</hi> And: <hi>Quem fugiam ſcio, ad quem fugiam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcio: I knovv vvhom I ſhould fly: but I knovv not to vvhom to flye.</hi> O but we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to obey our Prince: I neede not tell you how ſarre, and in what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees: <hi>S. Peter</hi> and <hi>S. Iohn</hi> tell you by their example the caſe muſte be limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. I will onely put you in mynd of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthy men ſometyme Prelates in the Church, and as it were houlde you the booke to reade howe they haue delt with Princes and potentates
<note place="margin">Act. 6.19.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:71"/>vpon the like occaſion: what veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſwaſions, how manifeſtly they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted for his ſake: <hi>VVho is terrible and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth avvay the ſpirit of Princes,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.</note> terrible to the Kings of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodoretus</hi> wryteth thus:
<note place="margin">Ec. hiſto. lb. 4. ca. 17</note> 
               <hi>Cum Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus</hi> (Modeſtus) <hi>Caeſaream veniſſet, Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Magnum accercitum honorificè excipit, leui &amp; blanda oratione compellat: hortatur vt cedat tempori, &amp; ue propter nimis curioſam dogmat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m obſeruationem, eamque paruo eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandam, tot tantasque eccleſias prodat: polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetur ſe Imperatoris</hi> (Valentis) <hi>amicitiam ei conciliaturum beneficiaque multis aliis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de euentura praedica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cui diuinus ille vir: pueris (inquit) haec quidem oratio conuenit, ſiquidem illi ac ſui ſimiles eiuſmodi verba a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidé arripiunt: at qui ſunt in ſacris literis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducati, ne vnam quidem ſillabam diuinorum dogmatum prodi ſiaunt: ſed pro iſtorum defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione, ſi opus ſit, nullum non mortis genus liben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter amplectuntur: quod autem ad Imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris amicitiam attinet, eam cum pietate iunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam magni aeſtimo, ſed ſi ea careat, pernicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſſe dico. &amp;c. VVhen the Lieutenante
<pb facs="tcp:2674:72"/>vvas come to Ceſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, he called for Baſill the great, and receaued him honorably, and by a ſvveete and gentle ſpeach exhorted him to yelde to the tyme, and not vpon to curious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of ſome poynte of no great vvayght to betray ſo many and ſo great churches, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing him vvithall to reconcile him to the Emperours fauour, and affirming that much good might come thereof to many. To vvhom this diuyne man anſvvered, that his tale vvere fit to perſvvade children and ſuch like, vvhich vvould eaſely lyke of ſuch offers: but that thoſe vvhich are brought vppe in holy vvrit, can not ſuffer one fillable of heauenly doctrine and lavves to be betrayed, but for defence thereof vvould embrace, if neede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any kinde of death. As for the amitye of the Emperour, if it might be had vvith pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etye, I much vvould eſteeme it, but vvithout that I ſaye it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> May it pleaſe you to reade a litle after the conſtante confeſſion of the Preiſts and Deacons of <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 4. ca. 20.</note> being exhorted by <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the Count: <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> fidem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis per Patrum ſucceſſionem traditam prode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:72"/>affirmando Valenten Auguſtinum Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratorem clementiſſimum hac re veheme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter delectatum iri. Poſtremó cum maxima con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentione vocis haec verba protulit: O miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri, obſequimini. Ariani opinioni aſſentite. Nam diuinum numen, licet illa quam colitis religio vera ſit, ſi non veſtra ſponte, ſed neceſſitate ducti ab ea diſcedatis, veniam vobis daturum eſt: Etenim in his quae neceſſitate peccantur, relinquitur excuſationi locus, ſed cum ſua ſponte quiſquam deliquerit, carere reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione, non poteſt. To betraye their Aunceſtors fayth receaued of the Apoſtlis by ſucceſſion of the Fathers, affirming that Valens the moſte clemente Emperour vvoulde be much pleaſed thereby. Laſtely vvith greate vehemency of ſpeach &amp; loude voice be vttered theſe vvorde: O miſerable men, obey, aſſent to the Arians opinion, for though your religion vvere true, the diuyne Maieſtye vvould pardon, ſeeing you fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from it vvillingly, but of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity compelled: for their is euer iuſte exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe to them that offend by neceſſity, though vvhen a man falleth vvillingly he can not be vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blame.</hi> Reade the place and marke
<pb facs="tcp:2674:73"/>how litle they eſteemed theſe World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaſions, which I haue therefore recyted at large, becauſe the worlde is prone now a dayes, not only to vſe, but alſo to follow the lyke inchaunte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>But muſt the Prince needs be ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed? Then <hi>Symeones</hi> an Archbiſhop of <hi>Perſie</hi> is without cauſe prayſed in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ozo. lib. 2. ca. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Qui introductus ad Sap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Regem vt de fide ſua reſponderet, neque veritus eſt quiequam, neque Regem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orauit: Rex commotus ſciſcitatur cur iam neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pſum adoret, cum ante feciſſet. Cui Symcones, non ante (inquit) eram deductus ad verum Deum prodendum, &amp; propterea non re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſ tham debitos honores Regi praeſtare: at iam idem ipſum facere fas non eſt, nam iam pro pietate &amp; noſtra religione decertaturus venio. VVho being brought to King Sapor to gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n accompt of his fayth, neither vvas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vvhit afrayd, neither adored the Kinge: vvhereat the King being offended, demaunded vvhy be novv did not his duty to him as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tymes before he had done? To vvhom Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon,
<pb facs="tcp:2674:73"/>I vvas not ſayed he before brought to your preſence to renounce the true God, and therefore then I refuſed not to doe due honour to the Kinge, but novv it is not lavvfull to doe the ſame, for novv I come to combat for piety and our religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus to obſerue tymes (M. Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor) was good wiſdome ſo to honour the Prince at one tyme, that God be not diſhonored at an other tyme.
<note place="margin">Luc. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> This was to <hi>render to Ceſar the thinges that are Ceſars: and the thinges that are Gods, to God.</hi> O that all Prelates, in worldly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration worthy men, would learne by theſe examples and the lyke, to teach Princes, rather then to be taught by them, to be ſtout in God his cauſe: and ſo happily to winne both the Prince and the people, rather then by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to peruerte them. Will you haue an example of ſuch lamentable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents:
<note place="margin">Theod. lib. 4. ca. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Vlphilas Gotthorum Epiſcopus cuius verba pro ratis legibus habebant, cum ab Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxio pecuniae illecebris perſuaſus eſſet, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam doctrinae eſſe differentiam (Catholicorum
<pb facs="tcp:2674:74"/>&amp; Arianorum) idem barbaris ſuis ſua autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate potiús quam ratione vlla ita perſuaſit, vt patrem maiorem quidem dicant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam tamen eſſe filium noluit dicere. Vlphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Biſhop of the Gothes vvhoſe vvordes the people compted of as of very lavves, being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted of Eudoxius by mony, ſo perſvvaded thoſe his barberous men, not by any reaſon but by his authoritye onely, that betvvixte the Catholicks and the Arians their vvas in doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine no difference: that they affirme the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be greater then the ſonne, but yet vvill not ſay that the ſonne is a creature.</hi> Lyke as if an hereticke Superintendent ſhould aſke a diſſemlinge Catholicke: doeſt thou beleeue, that Chriſt is in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament? No forſooth: and ſayth no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, but meaneth he is not there vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſibly and fleſhly: were not this to ſay as the hereticke woulde haue? And if ſome learned man would teach in this eaſe that he might ſay ſo verve well, were it not a damnable leſſon both to Maiſter and Scholler? Your learning &amp; your wiſdome knoweth it were ſo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2674:74"/>
            <p>But will you geue me leaue to bring one example more of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples dangerous error through the ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous demeanure of Catholicke Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates? <hi>Miſinus &amp; Vitalis</hi> ſent to Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople from the Biſhop of Rome to examine the caſe of one <hi>Peter</hi> eſteemed an hereticke, delte ſo couldly in the matter, and kept ſuch familiar compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with the hereticks:
<note place="margin">Euang. lib. 3. ca. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Vt ea ratione mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſimplices homines ab hereticis in errorem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducerentur qui affirmare non dubitarunt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum ab Epiſcopo Romano in communionem receptum eſſe. That by their meenes, many ſimple men vvere brought into errour by the hereticks, vvho ſticked not to affirme that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vvas admitted, by the Biſhop of Rome to his Communion.</hi> And becauſe I ſpake of ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lding to Princes, the ſelfe ſame hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory telleth that <hi>Acacius</hi> the Biſhop of Conſtantinople (otherwiſe a worthy man) was iudged by the Councell of Calced on <hi>grauiſsimo crimine dignus, vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a moſt greeuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fault,</hi> becauſe he did not tell <hi>Zeno</hi> the Emperor which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb facs="tcp:2674:75"/>with <hi>Peter,</hi> the Councells ſentence vpon him. <hi>Cume rte iſtud ſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do amaret Zeaonem,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cap.</note> preſtare deberet: verum Imperatoris deſiderio ſatiſfacere quam fidei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conſulere expetebat. VVhen perdy, if he had loued the Emperour Zeno, he ſhould haue done that, but he had a greater deſire to ſatiſfy the Emperours mynd, then to aduaunce the fayth.</hi> He ſaw that the Emperour had prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, and therefore to gratifie his Maieſty, diſſembled what was done in the Councell, and him ſelfe communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with him. But it was ſmall for the Emperours honour to haue ſuch a freend that would not deale plainlye, as it appeareth by the ſtory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Themiſtius</hi> the Philoſofer ſpeaking of the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acians,</hi> that applied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the Emperours pleaſure (then Ioui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus) agaynſt their conſcience, ſayth: <hi>Aſſentatores non Deum ſed purpuram Colu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe,
<note place="margin">Socrat. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ca. 21.</note> Euripoque ſimilis eſſe, qui modò in hanc, modò in illam partem praecipitatur. That thoſe flatterers did not vvorſhip God, but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: and vvere lyke to Euripus, vvhich
<pb facs="tcp:2674:75"/>runneth one vvhyle this vvaye, an other vvhyle that vvay.</hi> Vndoubtedly beſides that, ſimulation is an horrible offence toward God, beſides the euell exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples miniſtred thereby, to the ſimple, and the puniſhment due for ſo many ſoules miſcaried: vndowtedly I ſaye a knowne diſſembler is neuer well thought of: yea he is alwayes ſecretly miſliked of the ſame Potentats whom he thinketh by ſoothing and yeelding to gratifie. And it is certen that among them ſelues they ieſt at ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfaits. As <hi>Octauius. Auguſtus</hi> drinking to a fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his taxed one that ſate preſent, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Proditionem amo, Proditores non l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udo.</hi> I loue the betraying of treaſon, but I doe not prayſe the betrayers thereof.</p>
            <p>And here I remember the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtorye of <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> the falſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Conſtantinople, Who hauing yelded to the Emperout againſt Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and vtterly abiuring them, and conſented to the excommunication of <hi>Iohn Chriſoroas</hi> (otherwiſe) <hi>S. Dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2674:76"/>and other holy men for the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, notwithſtanding, fell into ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure and diſgrace, that as it is long, ſo it is lothſome and pittifull to tell what diſhonotable reproche he ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before all the people where he had bene Biſhop, not one of them all mourning or lamentinge his caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his inconſtancy and dublenes: for euen vntill his miſerable death the wretched man ſayed, whatſoeuer they would haue him, hoping thereby to wynne fauour, but it full out farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſisimp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Imperator p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triciis, ſignificate, dicens: Quid di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de noſtra &amp; Concil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (inqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) &amp; credis, &amp; hone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abhor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t conſcſtim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſpondentes di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erunt e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> audire nolunius de Rspan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pollu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, exho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ergo vadi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in terebr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, &amp; ſic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſententia, deſcendit ad clauſtra firarum &amp; decollatrus eſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to him certen of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> cauſed him to be queſtioned vvithall thus: VVhat ſayeſt thou of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the
<pb facs="tcp:2674:76"/>Councell that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove held? You beleeue vvell Sir ſayeth he, and the Councell vvas good, thinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by theſe vvordes to pleaſe the Emperour: but they ſtrayght anſvvered him, vve vvill not beare theſe thinges of thy pollured mouth: from benceforth therfore go dovvne into darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſo bauing that ſentence geuen vpon him, he deſcended into the places vvhere vvild beaſts vſe to be kept, and there vvas behedded.</hi> So that in this man (as in all doble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets) is and ſhall be verified the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie:
<note place="margin">Sophon. 1</note> 
               <hi>I vvill deſtroy thoſe vvhich ſvveare by our Lord, &amp; by Melchom:</hi> By their Lord God in hart, and the Idoll, or (as in the hebrew) in their King with tonge and lippes.</p>
            <p>Contrarywyſe when a graue Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late will deale playnly and reſiſte the fancy of his Prince, although he might thereby incurre diſpleaſure, that thing hath greater commodities then may eaſely be eſteemed: that is, ſo glorious in heauen, and heroicall vpon earth, as might moue a man in many reſpectes exceedingly. To omit all others, the
<pb facs="tcp:2674:77"/>aboue named <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſhall ſuffice to declare what wiſdome it is, in tyme and place mildly to mortifie the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces humor. Whoe being aſked of the Emperour (named alſo <hi>Conſtantine</hi>) <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quid nos laederet, ſi dixerimus</hi> Theotòkon Chriſtotòkon:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>At ille hunc complexus, ait: Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere domine, ne ad contagionem tuam venit ſermo iſte. Nonne vides qualiter deuulgetur &amp; anathematizetur Neſtorius a tota eccleſia? Qui reſpondens, ait: I go diſcere volens inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogaui, verum vſque ad te ſermo. VVell, vvhat burte vvould it doe vs, if vve ſhould call our B. Lady the mother of Chriſt?</hi> (For the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks called her Gods mother, and the Neſtorians would not ſo doe, but called her Chriſts mother onely) <hi>But the Biſhop Conſtantine embracing the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſayed: Oh my Lord haue pitye, let not that terme be vſed to thy defiling: doeſt thou not ſee, hovv Neſtorius is publiſhed and proclaymed as accurſed by the vvhole Church? VVhoe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvered and ſayed: I aſked the queſtion but for my learning only, it vvas but to thee ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi> Is it not very playne here, that if
<pb facs="tcp:2674:77"/>the Patriarch had ſoothed him in this as he did afterwardes in other things a great parte of the worlde had bene in danger of Neſtoriſme? But when he heard the matter gayneſayed, he excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him ſelfe and was aſhamed that he had moued the queſtion: Such a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue it is to deale diſcreatly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly betweene God and Princes, that we alwayes remember:
<note place="margin">1. pſ. 117.</note> 
               <hi>It is good rather to hope in our Lord, then to hope in Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I haue rudely and breifely, but truly and charitably ſet downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes dyuers examples, if it may pleaſe God to geue you heauenly vnderſtandinge by ſome one or other of them to ſee your owne faulte and to repent before the dreadfull accompte which you muſt needs make, ſo much the ſooner the elder that you are. Doe not conceaue I beſeech you that by theſe ſundry hiſtories I meante to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crybe your perſon, good M. Doctor take me not amiſſe. If by the vniuerſal vew of other mens noughtye demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure
<pb facs="tcp:2674:78"/>you doe the better perceaue what ſoeuer little or greate faulte is in your ſelfe (as by the Preachers generall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, we doe all the better eſpye our owne defects) that is my meaning, that was my purpoſe. If my manner of vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance doe offende, pardon lacke of ſkill, or thincke that I was rather oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied about the matter, then curious in the arte. If you will needs thincke that I touch you ſometyme more then was neede: let the chidings of a frende preuayle more with your good nature and wiſdome, then the kiſſes of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemye.</p>
            <p>For learning or wiſdome, I am not worthy to counſell you, but of duety and good will I preſume to exhorte you, ſo earneſtly as I doe ſincerely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and loue you, that you conſider your calling: A Preiſt, a Doctor, a man of worſhip, of eſtimation. What could Chriſt haue done more for you then he hath done?
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 215.</note> 
               <hi>VVhat then vvill you ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to our Lorde, for all that he hath rendred
<pb facs="tcp:2674:78"/>to you:</hi> Will you dye for his ſake?
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus promptus, caro infirma: The ſpirit is prompt, but the fleſh is infirme.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 22.</note> That is not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at your hand. <hi>Non dum vſque ad ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem reſiſtimus: vve haue not yet reſiſted vnto bloud.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Will you forſake all and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a beggar? <hi>Si vis perfectuss eſſe, vade &amp; vende omnia &amp; ſequere me: If thou vvilt be perfecte, goe ſell the things that thou haſte, and folovve me.</hi> But neither is that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. Wil you ſuffer impriſonment?
<note place="margin">Act. 16.</note> And at midnight <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, did prayſe God: when their ſeete were faſt in the ſtocks in the inner pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But we ſee that many earneſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks haue alſo their libertie. Will you goe into baniſhment and lyue in a Catholicke countrye?
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> 
               <hi>VVhen they ſhall perſecute you in this countrye, flye into an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And yet a man with wiſdome may lyue alſo quietly at home. Will you then for Chriſt his ſake leaue your ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings onely, and lyue ſtill worſhipful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon your ſtocke? To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould your peace vnleſſe you be vrged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o confeſſe
<pb facs="tcp:2674:79"/>your fayth: to prefer hereſie, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it neither by worde nor deede? What may a man doe leſſe that will do any thing for his ſweete Sauiour and mercifull redeemer?
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 19.16.</note> 
               <hi>VVhat permutation ſhall a man geue for his ſoule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you had liued in the primitiue world when you muſt either haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed Chriſt, or ſuffer a long death full of exqueſite torments, what woulde you haue done? whereas now ſo little loſſe a little before the tyme of ſome little temporalities, maketh you not only deny your religion, but to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine the contrary?
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uc. 12.48.</note> and yet you can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member well: much ſhalbe required of him that hath much.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 6</note> And <hi>Potentes Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tormenta Patientur. The mightye ſhall mightily ſuffer torments.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uc. 17.1.</note> And: <hi>VVo to him by vvhom ſcandalls come.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 13.</note> And <hi>ſhall they not all knovv that vvorke vvickednes that deuoure my people as they vvould eat bread?</hi> And S. Auſten.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. pſ. 52.</note> 
               <hi>Cum ſcis malum eſſe quod facis et ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men facis, nonne viuus deſcendis ad inſeros? vvhen thou dooſt knovv that that is ill vvhich
<pb facs="tcp:2674:79"/>thou dooſt and yet for all that dooſt it, dooſt thou not goe dovvne to hell, aliue?</hi> But I will not haue you feare onely: <hi>Perfecta charitas,
<note place="margin">1.10.4.18.</note> foras mittit timorem. Perfect charitie caſteth out feare.</hi> Good M. Doctor as you are not without cauſe eſteemed wiſe, ſo employ it to his honour who giueth all wiſdome. Be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be a foole to the world, that you may become hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wyſe. S. <hi>Ambroſe. S. Bafill. S. Chriſoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome</hi> were wiſe men, thinke what they haue done long a goe, and would doe in your caſe. Follow them, and be not ſeruant to them, that are the ſeruants of noughtines: that ſay in effect, <hi>Eda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus et bibamus, cras moriemur.
<note place="margin">1. Co. 15.32.</note> Let vs eate and drincke for to morrovv vve ſhall dye.</hi> Yf that were the way to heauen, to followe all worldes, all rellgions, all Princes, to be ſtill in fauour, to ſleepe in a whole ſkynne, to looſe nothing which way ſoeuer the winde bloweth. Suerly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men could wiſely doe all this, that nowe are eſteemed for very fooles: but of ſuch as in the laſt Iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:2674:80"/>ſhall howle and crye out for very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and confuſion:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 5.</note> 
               <hi>VVe ſenſeleſſe eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med their life madnes, and their ende vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out honor: Behould hovv they are compted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the children of God, and their lott is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This that I haue ſaid is in truth nothing, in reſpect of the matter, but in reſpect of your wiſdome it is much. I beſeech God to add more then I can vtter or think,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 26.</note> of his holy ſpirit which may leade you, <hi>In ſemitam rectam &amp; oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat tibi viam in qua ambules:</hi> in the right path, and ſhewe you the waye in the which you ought to walke. As for me, I am in this caſe to you as one that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the candle or opening the gate before his maſter. I ſeeke no thanke by this my ſeruice, as knoweth God: one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I quake to thinke of my friends dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: and therfore I crye out vnto you and make a noyſe, ſuch as I can in this my infancie.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Nam neque qui plantat eſt aliquid, neque qui rigat ſed quidat incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, Deus. For nether he that planteth is
<pb facs="tcp:2674:80"/>any thing, nor be that vvatereth, but be that geueth the increaſe, God.</hi> Chriſt our Sauiour keepe your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp in longe and good health.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The 15 of October. 1575.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
